Installing and using the binary distribution

The binary release comes as a .zip archive that includes Kawa itself (as a .jar file kawa-version.jar), some third-party helper libraries, kawa command scripts (for GNU/Linux/Unix/MacOS or Windows), and documentation (basically this manual).

After downloading (see Getting Kawa), extract the files from the .zip archive using a suitable unzip program, which will create a directory kawa-version, with lib, bin, and doc sub-directories. In the following, we assume the environment variable KAWA_HOME refers to this directory:

unzip ~/Downloads/kawa-version.zip
export KAWA_HOME=`pwd`/kawa-version

The binary release requires Java 7 or later. Java 8 is recommended. (Java 8 is needed for the JLine input editor, which is recommended for the REPL.) If you have an older Java implementation, or build for a mobile environment like Android, then you will need to get the source distribution.

If you want to use Kawa as part of some other application, you just need the $KAWA_HOME/lib/kawa.jar.

Running the kawa command

To run a Kawa script file or the Kawa read-eval-print-loop run the Kawa application. There are various way to do so.

The recommended way is to execute the $KAWA_HOME/bin/kawa Bash shell script. This should work on most Unix-like platforms that have Bash installed, including GNU/Linux, BSD, MacOS, and Cygwin/MingW. (Please report if you have problems.)

The script assumes that either a suitable java program is in your PATH; or the JAVA environment variable names a suitable java executable; or that JAVA_HOME is set so $JAVA_HOME/bin/java is suitable.

If you want to put kawa in your search path you can of course do:

PATH=$KAWA_HOME/bin:$PATH

Alternatively you can create a symbolic link in an already-searched directory. For example:

cd /usr/local/bin
ln -s $KAWA_HOME/bin/kawa kawa

The bin/kawa.bat script works on Windows.

Both scripts add some helper libraries, including support for input editing.

It is also possible to run Kawa using java directly:

java -jar $KAWA_HOME/lib/kawa.jar

or:

CLASSPATH=$KAWA_HOME/lib/kawa.jar
export CLASSPATH
java kawa.repl

On Windows:

set classpath=%KAWA_HOME%\lib\kawa.jar

To run Kawa in a fresh window use the -w flag:

kawa -w

or

java kawa.repl -w

Reading the documentation

The file doc/kawa-manual.epub contains the Kawa documention packaged as an electronic book, which is readable by most e-book readers. Plugins are also available for common browsers, for example EPUBReader for firefox.

Even easier is to invoke bin/kawa --browse-manual (or on Windows: bin\kawa.bat --browse-manual).

An epub is essentially a zip archive, which you can unzip:

cd $KAWA_HOME/doc
unzip kawa-manual.epub

Then you can use a plain browser with the URL file:$KAWA_HOME/doc/OEBPS/index.xhtml.

Up: Getting and installing Kawa

Previous: Getting and running Java

Next: Installing and using the source distribution

Installing Kawa programs as CGI scripts

The recommended way to have a web-server run a Kawa program as a CGI script is to compile the Kawa program to a servlet (as explained in Server-side scripts, and then use Kawa’s supplied CGI-to-servlet bridge.

First, compile your program to one or more class files as explained in Server-side scripts. For example:

kawa --servlet --xquery -C hello.xql

Then copy the resulting .class files to your server’s CGI directory. On Red Hat GNU/Linux, you can do the following (as root):

cp hello*.class /var/www/cgi-bin/

Next find the cgi-servlet program that Kawa builds and installs. If you installed Kawa in the default place, it will be in /usr/local/bin/cgi-servlet. (You’ll have this if you installed Kawa from source, but not if you’re just using Kawa .jar file.) Copy this program into the same CGI directory:

cp /usr/local/bin/cgi-servlet /var/www/cgi-bin/

You can link instead of copying:

ln -s /usr/local/bin/cgi-servlet /var/www/cgi-bin/

However, because of security issues this may not work, so it is safer to copy the file. However, if you already have a copy of cgi-servlet in the CGI-directory, it is safe to make a hard link instead of making an extra copy.

Make sure the files have the correct permissions:

chmod a+r /var/www/cgi-bin/hello*.class /var/www/cgi-bin/hello
chmod a+x /var/www/cgi-bin/hello

Now you should be able to run the Kawa program, using the URL http://localhost/cgi-bin/hello. It may take a few seconds to get the reply, mainly because of the start-up time of the Java VM. That is why servlets are preferred. Using the CGI interface can still be useful for testing or when you can’t run servlets.

Up: Working with XML and HTML

Previous: Installing web page scripts as Servlets

Next: Functions for accessing HTTP requests

Compatibility with standards

Kawa implements all the required and optional features of R7RS, with the following exceptions.

The entire “numeric tower" is implemented. However, some transcendental functions only work on reals. Integral functions do not necessarily work on inexact (floating-point) integers. (The whole idea of “inexact integer" in R5RS seems rather pointless ...)

Also, call-with-current-continuation is only “upwards" (?). I.e. once a continuation has been exited, it cannot be invoked. These restricted continuations can be used to implement catch/throw (such as the examples in R4RS), but not co-routines or backtracking.

Kawa now does general tail-call elimination, but only if you use the flag --full-tail-calls. (Currently, the eval function itself is not fully tail-recursive, in violation of R5RS.) The --full-tail-calls flag is not on by default, partly because it is noticably slower (though I have not measured how much), and partly I think it is more useful for Kawa to be compatible with standard Java calling conventions and tools. Code compiled with --full-tail-calls can call code compiled without it and vice versa.

Even without --full-tail-calls, if the compiler can prove that the procedure being called is the current function, then the tail call will be replaced by a jump. This includes must “obvious” cases of calls to the current function named using define or letrec, and many cases of mutual tail-recursion (including state-machines using letrec).

By default, symbols are case sensitive.

Kawa implements most of the features of the expression language of DSSSL, the Scheme-derived ISO-standard Document Style Semantics and Specification Language for SGML. Of the core expression language, the only features missing are character properties, external-procedure, the time-relationed procedures, and character name escapes in string literals. From the full expression language, Kawa additionally is missing format-number, format-number-list, and language objects. Quantities, keyword values, and the expanded lambda form (with optional and keyword parameters) are supported.

Up: Features

Previous: Implemented SRFIs

Frequently Asked Questions

What is the equivalent of Java import?

To provide a short name for a class instead of the complete fully-qualified name use either define-alias (or define-private-alias) or the import-class combination. For example, to be able to write ArrayList instead of java.util.ArrayList do either:

(import (class java.util ArrayList))

or

(define-alias ArrayList java.util.ArrayList)

Using import is recommended: It handles errors better, and it allows you to define multiple aliases conveniently:

(import (class java.util Map HashMap))

Both forms allow renaming. For example if you want to refer to java.lang.StringBuilder as StrBuf do:

(import (class java.lang (StringBuilder StrBuf)))

or:

(define-alias StrBuf java.lang.StringBuilder)

The name(s) defined by import are by default private. A name defined using define-alias is by default exported; to avoid that use define-private-alias instead.

You can also use define-namespace to introduce an abbreviation or renaming of a class name, but as a matter of style define-alias is preferred.

There is no direct equivalent to Java’s import PackageOrTypeName.* (type-import-on-demand) declaration, but you can alias a package:

(define-alias jutil java.util)
(define mylist :: jutil:List (jutil:ArrayList))

To import a static member, giving it a shortened name (like Java’s static-import-on-demand declaration), you can use define-alias. For example:

(define-alias console java.lang.System:console)

For static fields only (not methods or member classes) you can use an import form, either:

(import (only (java lang System) out))

or:

(import (only java.lang.System out))

This works because Kawa can treat any class as a “library”; in which case it considers all public static fields as exported bindings.

How do I refer to a Java member (nested) class?

Consider the Java SE member class javax.swing.text.AbstractDocument.Content. Using the Java syntax doesn’t work in Kawa. Inside you should use Kawa’s colon operator:

javax.swing.text.AbstractDocument:Content

Alternatively, you can use the internal JVM class name:

javax.swing.text.AbstractDocument$Content

Why does Kawa’s REPL use display rather than write?

The read-eval-print-loop of most Scheme implementations prints the evaluation result using write, while Kawa uses display by default.

First note that it is easy to override the default with the --output-format command-line option:

$kawa --output-format readable-scheme
#|kawa:1|# "abc"
"abc"

The reason display is the default is because of a vision of the REPL console as more than just printing out Scheme objects in textual form for use by a programmer. Some examples:

A math program can display equations and graphs as the output of an expression.

An expression can evaluate to a "picture" which would be displayed inline.

An HTML/XML obj can be insert into the output in visual form if the console understands HTML. (There is a prototype for this that works by using the JavaFX WebView as the display.)

The plan for "Kawa-shell" functionality is to have expressions that evaluate to process objects, which would be lazy strings. This string would be the data from standard output. Thus the effect of displaying a process object would be to print out the standard output - just like a regular shell. Users would find it confusing/annoying if shell output used quotes.

This "repl-as-pad" model doesn’t work as well if the repl uses write rather than display.

Up: Part . Reference Documentation

Previous: Miscellaneous topics

Next: The Kawa language framework

Features

Runs on the Java platform, with no native code needed.

Extends the Scheme language, following the R7RS specification from 2013. Scheme has many implementations, and is much used in research and teaching.

Programs run fast - roughly as fast as Java programs, and much faster than other “scripting languages”. This is due to a sophisticated compiler, compile-time transformations, type inference, and optional type declarations.

Full, convenient, and efficient access to the huge set of Java libraries means you can access objects, methods, fields, and classes without run-time overhead.

Start-up times are fast. You don’t have to wait for a lot of initialization. Even if you start with source code, the parser and compiler are fast.

Scripts are simple Kawa source files that can run as an application or command. These are simple to write, start, and run efficiently, since they’re automatically compiled before execution.

Alternatively, you can embed Kawa as a scripting language for Java applications.

Deployment is easy and flexible. You just need the Kawa jar file.

Macros and custom named literals make it easy to extend the syntax and implement Domain-Specific Languages.

Kawa provides the usual read-eval-print loop, as well as batch modes.

Kawa has builtin pretty-printer support, and fancy formatting.

Kawa supports class-definition facilities, and separately-compiled modules.

You can allocate and initialize objects with a compact “builder” syntax. It works out-of-the-box (with no run-time overhead) on many classes and APIs, but can be customized if need be.

A library for functional composable pictures lets you create “picture” objects, display them, transform them, combine them, convert to SVG or images, and more. This can be “printed” directly in the Kawa console (either the DomTerm console or the Swing one).

JavaFX programming is simpler.

You can run Kawa programs on Android, and there is special handling to make constructing View objects easier.

Flexible shell-like functionality, including process literals.

Web page scripts are easy to write and install with self-configuring web servers, optionally using servlets and XML literals.

Arrays and sequences have a lot of flexibility: Arrays can be multi-dimensional; you can use an array as an index (which generalizes slices and permutations); you can define a lazy array using a function that maps indexes to values; you can re-map the indexes to yield a transformed array.

Many useful features for mathematics and numerics:

The full “numeric tower” includes infinite-precision rational numbers and complex numbers.

Compile-time optimization of arithmetic with the use of type declarations and inference.

A quantity is a real number with a unit, such as 3cm.

Quaternions are a 4-dimensional generalization of complex numbers. Unsigned primitive integer types (ubyte, ushort, uint, ulong) are implemented efficiently without object allocation.

A lazy value wraps an expression which is evaluated only when it is needed.

Kawa provides a framework for implementing other programming languages, and comes with incomplete support for CommonLisp, Emacs Lisp, and EcmaScript, and XQuery.

Implemented SRFIs
Compatibility with standards

Up: The Kawa Scheme language

Previous: News - Recent Changes

Next: The Kawa Community

Generic (dynamically overloaded) procedures

A generic procedure is a collection of method procedures. (A "method procedure" is not the same as a Java method, but the terms are related.) You can call a generic procedure, which selects the "closest match" among the component method procedures: I.e. the most specific method procedure that is applicable given the actual arguments.

Warning: The current implementation of selecting the "best" method is not reliable if there is more than one method. It can select depending on argument count, and it can select between primitive Java methods. However, selecting between different Scheme procedures based on parameter types should be considered experimental. The main problem is we can’t determine the most specific method, so Kawa just tries the methods in order.

Procedure: make-procedure [keyword: value]... method...

Create a generic procedure given the specific methods. You can also specify property values for the result.

The keywords specify how the arguments are used. A method: keyword is optional and specifies that the following argument is a method. A name: keyword specifies the name of the resulting procedure, when used for printing. Unrecognized keywords are used to set the procedure properties of the result.

(define plus10 (make-procedure foo: 33 name: 'Plus10
                            method: (lambda (x y) (+ x y 10))
                            method: (lambda () 10)))

Up: Procedures

Previous: Procedure properties

Next: Extended Formal Arguments List

Ideas and tasks for contributing to Kawa

Kawa (like other Free Software projects) has no lack of tasks and projects to work on. Here are some ideas.

The ones marked (GSoC) are probably most suitable for a Google Summer of Code project, in being a reasonable size, self-contained, and not depending on other tasks.

Run interactive process in separate Java Virtual Machine:

(GSoC)

When developing and testing it is useful for the REPL to support hot-swapping (replacing functions on-the-fly) and debugging. The main goal being able to smoothly reload changed modules (files or functions), and have other modules not break. Debugging (such as setting breakpoints) would not be a priority for this project, but could be a follow-on project. Skills: Should be experienced with Java, and interested in learning about JVM TI and similar low-level parts of the platform. Difficulty: Challenging, but you can study how Java-9’s new jshell uses the JVM TI.

Better dynamic reload

(GSoC - this is related to the previous item)

Kawa does a lot of optimizations and inlining. This conflicts with being able to “reload” a module into an already-running interactive environment.

We could add an option to load a module in “reloadable” mode. Kawa already patches an old function object (a ModuleMethod) so existing references to the function get automatically updated. However, there are problems if the “signature” of the function changes - for example if the return type (declared or inferred) becomes more general. In those cases the best thing is to re-compile any code that depends on the modified function.

Reloading a module that defines a class is even trickier, at least if there are existing instances that should work as the updated class. We can handle the special case where only method bodies change: In reloadable mode, each method body is compiled to a separate function, the actual body indirects to the function. We must also recognize when compiling a new version of the same class, which requires a textual comparison between the old and new versions, or a structural comparison between the old class and the new code.

When it comes to top-level variables, an issue is when to re-evaluate the initializing expression. It is reasonable to do so if and only if the expression is modified, which again requires a textual comparison.

Easier Access to Native Libraries using JNA/JNR

(GSoC)

The traditional way to access native (C/C++) functions is using JNI, but it’s very awkward. JNA and JNR are much easier to use. This project would design and implement an easy-to-use Kawa wrapper for for JNR. You should study existing JNR wrappers, such as that for JRuby. Difficulty: Medium. Need to study existing wrappers and "foreign function interfaces" (in multiple languages) and design one suitable for Kawa. Some Scheme (Kawa) experience would be helpful.

Types for units

(GSoC)

Kawa supports units (such as cm^2 for square centimeters) and quantities (such as 4cm^2). We would like to integrate these into the type system, both for performance and compile-time type checking.

For syntax we can use a pseudo-parameterized type quantity. For example:

(define a1 ::quantity[cm^2] 4cm^2)
(* 2.0 a1) ;; ⇒ 8cm^2
(+ 2.0 a1) ;; compile-time error

The run-time type of the variable a1 should be a primitive double, without object allocation. Of course when a1 is converted to an object, we create a Quantity, not a Double. We can build on Kawa’s existing framework for non-standard primitive types such as character and ulong. Skills: Need good Java experience, and somewhat familiar with the Java Virtual Machine. You will need to become comfortable reading <code>javap</code> output. Difficulty: Modest.

Compiler should use class-file reading instead of reflection

The Kawa compiler currently uses reflection to determine properties (such as exported function definitions) from referenced classes. It would be better to read class files. This should not be too difficult, since the gnu.bytecode library abstracts over class information read by reflection or class reading.

Mutually dependent Java and Scheme modules

(GSoC - maybe)

We’d like a command for compiling a list of Java and Scheme source files that may have mutual dependencies. A good way to do this is to hook into javac, which is quite extensible and pluggable.

One could do something like:

Read the “header" of each Kawa source file, to determine the name of the generated main class.

Enter these class names into the javac tables as “uncompleted” classes.

Start compiling the Java files. When this requires the members of the Kawa classes, switch to the Kawa files. From javac, treat these as pre-compiled .class files. I.e. we treat the Kawa compiler as a black box that produces Symbols in the same way as reading class files. At this point we should only need the initial “scan” phase on Kawa.

If necessary, finish compiling remaining Kawa files.

This approach may not immediately provide as robust mixed-language support as is ideal, but it is more amenable to incremental improvement than a standalone stub-generator.

This project is good if you know or want to learn how javac works.

Use Java-7 MethodHandles and invokedynamic

Java 7 supports MethodHandles which are meant to provide better performance (ultimately) for dynamic languages. See JSR 292 and the Da Vinci Machine Project. Kawa makes limited use of MethodHandles, and no use of invokedynamic. There is more to be done. For example, we can start by optimizing arithmetic when the types are unknown at compile-time. They could make implementing generic functions (multimethods) more efficient. At some point we want to compile lambdas in the same way as Java 8 does. This can potentially be more efficient than Kawa’s current mechanism.

Remi Forax’s vmboiler is a small library on top of ASM that generates optimistically typed bytecodes. It could be useful for ideas.

Parameterized types

(GSoC)

Kawa has some limited support for parameterized types, but it’s not used much. Improve type inferencing. Support definition of parameterized classes. Better use of parameterized types for sequence class. Support wildcards. (It might be better to have wild-carding be associated with declarations, as in Scala or proposed for Java, rather than uses.) See also http://openjdk.java.net/jeps/8043488.

Optimized function types and values using MethodHandles

(GSoC)

Kawa doesn’t have true function types: Parameter and result types are only handled for “known” functions. The general case with optional and keyword parameter is complicated, but simple fixed-arity procedure types would be very useful.

The following syntax is suggested:

procedure[(T1 .. Tn) Tr]

T1 through T1 are types of the parameters, and Tr is the type of the result. For example: procedure[(vector int) string]. We call this a typed-procedure type (in contrast to plain procedure).

If a value has a typed-procedure type then its run-time representation is a just a MethodHandle. If such a procedure is called, the generated bytecode is to just call its invokeExact method. The argument expressions are converted (and type-checked) the same way as if we were calling a statically-known procedure.

Note that passing an int argument of to procedure[(vector int) string] value does not require allocating an object to “box” the int; we can pass a plain int as-is. Thus using typed-procedure types can lead to major speed-up. For example the lib-test.scm should become much faster.

Converting a known procedure to a typed-procedure type is usually just a matter of creating a MethodHandle that references the method implementing the procedure. Some glue code may be needed if the types aren’t identical, or if the procedure is a closure.

Converting a type-procedure value p to generic value (such as untyped procedure or object) can be though of as wrapping it in a lambda:

((lambda (arg1::vector arg2::int)::string (p arg1 arg2))

Coercing a generic value or an untyped procedure to a typed-procedure would need to generate a method whose signature matches the typed-procedure type, and in the body of the method use a generic apply.

Coercing from one typed-procedure type to a different typed-procedure type is a combination of the above techniques (as if converting first to object and then to the target type), though some optimizations are worth doing.

Adding varargs support can be done later.

We need a fall-back mechanism for platforms (such as Android) that don’t support MethodHandles. The easiest is to just treat a typed-procedure type as plain procedure at run-time, though we still want the compile-time type-checking,

Full continuations

Currently being worked on.

Add support for full continuations, which is the major feature missing for Kawa to qualify as a “true Scheme”. One way to implement continuations is to add a add that converts the abstract syntax tree to continuation-passing-style, and then expand the existing full-tail-call support to manage a stack. There are other ways to solve the problem. This may benefit from Faster tailcalls.

Faster tailcalls

Make --full-tailcalls run faster. This may depend on (or incorporate) TreeList-optimization.

TreeList-optimization

The TreeList class is a data structure for “flattened” trees. It is used for XML-style nodes, for multiple values, and for the full-tail-call API. The basic concept is fine, but it could do with some re-thinking to make make random-access indexing fast. Also, support for updating is insufficient. (This needs someone into designing and hacking on low-level data-structures, along with lots of profiling and testing.)

Asynchronous evaluation

C# recently added asynch and await keywords for asynchronous programming. Kawa’s recently improved support for lazy programming seems like a good framework for equivalent functionality: Instead of an asynch method that returns a Task<T>, the Kawa programmer would write a function that returns a lazy[T]. This involves some design work, and modifying the compiler to rewrite the function body as needed.

This is related to full continuations, as the re-writing is similar.

REPL console and other REPL improvement

Currently being worked on.

Improvements to the read-eval-print console. In addition to a traditional Swing console, it would be useful to support using a web browser as a remote terminal, possibly using web-sockets. (This allows “printing” HTML-expressions, which can be a useful way to learn and experiment with web technologies.) See here for an article on the existing Swing REPL, along with some to-do items. Being able to hide and show different parts of the output might be nice. Being able to link from error messages to source might be nice. Better handling of redefinitions is discussed here in the context of JavaXF Script; this is a general REPL issue, mostly independent of the GUI for it.

An interesting possibility is to use the IPython framework. There are existing ports for Scala: either IScala or Scala Notebook.

XQuery-3.0 functionality

(GSoC, for some subset)

It would be nice to update the XQuery (Qexo) support to some subset of XQuery 3.0.

XQuery-updates

It would be nice to support XQuery updates. This depends on TreeList-optimization.

Common Lisp support

Kawa supports a small subset of the Common Lisp language, but it supports a much larger subset of core Common Lisp concepts and data structures, some designed with Common Lisp functionality in mind. Examples include packages, arrays, expanded function declarations, type specifications, and format. A lot could be done to improve the Common Lisp support with modest effort. Some Common Lisp features could also be useful for Scheme: Documentation strings (or markup) as Java annotations, better MOP-like introspection, and generic methods a la defmethod (i.e. with multiple definition statements, possibly in separate files, as opposed to the current make-procedure) all come to mind. Being able to run some existing Common Lisp code bases with at most modest changes should be the goal. One such package to start with might be an existing test framework, perhaps FivaAM. Full Common Lisp compatibility is nice, but let’s walk before we can run.

JEmacs improvements

(GSoC, for some subset)

A lot of work is needed to make JEmacs useful. One could try to import a useful package and see what works and what fails. Or one may look at basic editing primitives. Enhancements may be needed to core Emacs Lisp language primitives (enhancing Common Lisp support may help), or to the display engine.

Emacs now supports lexical bindings - we should do the same.

Improved IDE integration

There is some Kawa support for Eclipse (Schemeway), and possibly other IDEs (NetBeans, IntelliJ). But many improvements are desirable. REPL improvements may be a component of this.

Plugin for NetBeans IDE

Kawa-Scheme support for the NetBeans IDE would be useful. One could perhaps build on the Clojure plugin.

Plugin for Eclipse IDE

Kawa-Scheme support for the Eclipse IDE would be useful. Probably makes sense to enhance SchemeWay. It may also make sense to build on the Dynamic Languages Toolkit, possibly making use of Schemeide, though DLTk seems more oriented towards interpreted non-JVM-based languages.

Improve Emacs integration

SLIME is an Emacs mode that provides IDE-like functionality. It supports Kawa.

JDEE is a Java development environment, so might have better hooks to the JVM and Java debugging architecture.

CEDET is a more general framework of development tools.

Implement javax.tools and code-range support in Kawa compiler

Kawa currently records the line and column position of syntactic elements. For an IDE it is desirable to have both start and end position of an element, for example so it can put a squiggly line under an erroneous form.

Hop-style web programming

Hop is an interesting design for integrating server-side and client-side programming using a Scheme dialect. These ideas seem like they would port quite well to Kawa.

String localization

(GSoC)

Support localization by extending the SRFI_109 syntax, in the manner of (and compatible with) GNU gettext. I.e. optionally specify a localization key (to use as an index in the translation database); if there is no key specified, default to using the literal parts of the string.

Data binding

Implement a “bind” mechanism similar to that of JavaFX Script. The idea is that when you initialize a variable or field, instead of initializing it to a fixed value, you bind it to an expression depending on other variables. We install “listeners” on those variables, so when those variables change, we update the bound variable. This feature is useful in many applications, but the initial focus could be GUI programming and perhaps web programming.

Decimal arithmetic and repeated decimals

(GSoC. Possibly a bit light for a full Summer project, but can be extended or combined with other projects.)

Exact decimal arithmetic is a variation of exact rational arithmetic, but may be more user-friendly. In particular, printing using decimals is generally nicer than fractions. It is also sometimes useful to specify an explicit scale, so we can distinguish 0.2 from 0.20. We can use the Java BigDecimal class, but run into problems with division - for example (/ 1.0 3.0). We should implement a subclass of RatNum that generalizes BigDecimal to also handle repeating decimals. We need a lexical syntax for repeating decimals. Possible ideas: 0._81_ or 0.#81. If a Scheme number literal is specified as exact and has either a decimal point or an exponent (for example #e1.25), then it should read as an exact decimal, not a fraction.

Optional strict typing along with an explicit dynamic type

(GSoC)

Kawa currently implements “optimistic” typing: The compiler only complains if an expression has no values in common with the target type - for example, if assigning a string expression to an integer variable. It would be interesting to experiment with a --strict-typing option (which would never be the default): Strict typing would only allow “widening” conversions - i.e. that the expression type be a subtype of the target type. For example it would complain if assigning a number to an integer unless you used an explicit cast.

To make this easier to work with we’d make use of the dynamic type, similar to what C# does: Any expression can be converted to or from dynamic without the compiler complaining. Similarly, if x is dynamic then x:name is allowed by the compiler regardless of name, with all checking being deferred to run-time. If a variable is declared without a type, it should default to dynamic. The dynamic type is represented in the VM as object but with an annotation (like we do with character).

The type-checker might need some changes to better distinguish implicit conversions from explicit casts.

Run interactive process in separate Java Virtual Machine:
Better dynamic reload
Easier Access to Native Libraries using JNA/JNR
Types for units
Compiler should use class-file reading instead of reflection
Mutually dependent Java and Scheme modules
Use Java-7 MethodHandles and invokedynamic
Parameterized types
Optimized function types and values using MethodHandles
Full continuations
Faster tailcalls
TreeList-optimization
Asynchronous evaluation
REPL console and other REPL improvement
XQuery-3.0 functionality
XQuery-updates
Common Lisp support
JEmacs improvements
Improved IDE integration
Hop-style web programming
String localization
Data binding
Decimal arithmetic and repeated decimals
Optional strict typing along with an explicit dynamic type

Up: The Kawa Community

Previous: Projects using Kawa

Loading Java functions into Scheme

When kawa -C compiles (see Files compilation) a Scheme module it creates a class that implements the java.lang.Runnable interface. (Usually it is a class that extends the gnu.expr.ModuleBody.) It is actually fairly easy to write similar "modules" by hand in Java, which is useful when you want to extend Kawa with new "primitive functions" written in Java. For each function you need to create an object that extends gnu.mapping.Procedure, and then bind it in the global environment. We will look at these two operations.

There are multiple ways you can create a Procedure object. Below is a simple example, using the Procedure1 class, which is class extending Procedure that can be useful for one-argument procedure. You can use other classes to write procedures. For example a ProcedureN takes a variable number of arguments, and you must define applyN(Object[] args) method instead of apply1. (You may notice that some builtin classes extend CpsProcedure. Doing so allows has certain advantages, including support for full tail-recursion, but it has some costs, and is a bit trickier.)

import gnu.mapping.*;
import gnu.math.*;
public class MyFunc extends Procedure1
{
  // An "argument" that is part of each procedure instance.
  private Object arg0;

  public MyFunc(String name, Object arg0)
  {
    super(name);
    this.arg0 = arg0;
  }

  public Object apply1 (Object arg1)
  {
    // Here you can so whatever you want. In this example,
    // we return a pair of the argument and arg0.
    return gnu.lists.Pair.make(arg0, arg1);
  }
}

You can create a MyFunc instance and call it from Java:

  Procedure myfunc1 = new MyFunc("my-func-1", Boolean.FALSE);
  Object aresult = myfunc1.apply1(some_object);

The name my-func-1 is used when myfunc1 is printed or when myfunc1.toString() is called. However, the Scheme variable my-func-1 is still not bound. To define the function to Scheme, we can create a "module", which is a class intended to be loaded into the top-level environment. The provides the definitions to be loaded, as well as any actions to be performed on loading

public class MyModule
{
  // Define a function instance.
  public static final MyFunc myfunc1
    = new MyFunc("my-func-1", IntNum.make(1));
}

If you use Scheme you can use require:

#|kawa:1|# (require <MyModule>)
#|kawa:2|# (my-func-1 0)
(1 0)

Note that require magically defines my-func-1 without you telling it to. For each public final field, the name and value of the field are entered in the top-level environment when the class is loaded. (If there are non-static fields, or the class implements Runnable, then an instance of the object is created, if one isn’t available.) If the field value is a Procedure (or implements Named), then the name bound to the procedure is used instead of the field name. That is why the variable that gets bound in the Scheme environment is my-func-1, not myfunc1.

Instead of (require <MyModule>), you can do (load "MyModule") or (load "MyModule.class"). If you’re not using Scheme, you can use Kawa’s -f option:

$ kawa -f MyModule --xquery --
#|kawa:1|# my-func-1(3+4)
<list>1 7</list>

If you need to do some more complex calculations when a module is loaded, you can put them in a run method, and have the module implement Runnable:

public class MyModule implements Runnable
{
  public void run ()
  {
    Interpreter interp = Interpreter.getInterpreter();
    Object arg = Boolean.TRUE;
    interp.defineFunction (new MyFunc ("my-func-t", arg));
    System.err.println("MyModule loaded");
  }
}

Loading MyModule causes "MyModule loaded" to be printed, and my-func-t to be defined. Using Interpreter’s defineFunction method is recommended because it does the righ things even for languages like Common Lisp that use separate "namespaces" for variables and functions.

A final trick is that you can have a Procedure be its own module:

import gnu.mapping.*;
import gnu.math.*;
public class MyFunc2 extends Procedure2
{
  public MyFunc(String name)
  {
    super(name);
  }

  public Object apply2 (Object arg1, arg2)
  {
    return gnu.lists.Pair.make(arg1, arg2);
  }

  public static final MyFunc myfunc1 = new MyFunc("my-func-2);
}

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Using Java Arrays

Next: Evaluating Scheme expressions from Java

Mapping Scheme names to Java names

Programs use "names" to refer to various values and procedures. The definition of what is a "name" is different in different programming languages. A name in Scheme (and other Lisp-like languages) can in principle contain any character (if using a suitable quoting convention), but typically names consist of "words" (one or more letters) separated by hyphens, such as ‘make-temporary-file’. Digits and some special symbols are also used. Traditionally, Scheme is case-insensitive; this means that the names ‘loop’, ‘Loop’, and ‘LOOP’ are all the same name. Kawa is by default case-sensitive, but we recommend that you avoid using upper-case letters as a general rule.

The Java language and the Java virtual machine uses names for classes, variables, fields and methods. Names in the Java language can contain upper- and lower-case letters, digits, and the special symbols ‘_’ and ‘$’. The Java virtual machine (JVM) allows most characters, but still has some limitations.

Kawa translates class names, package names, field names, and local variable names using the ”symbolic” convention, so most characters are unchanged. For example the Scheme function ‘file-exists?’ becomes the field ‘file-exists?’, but dotted.name becomes ‘dotted\,name’. Such names may not be valid Java name, so to access them from a Java program you might have to use reflection.

When translating procedure names to method names, Kawa uses a different translation, in order to achieve more “Java-like” names. This means translating a Scheme-style name like ‘make-temporary-file’ to "mixed-case" words, such as ‘makeTemporaryFile’. The basic rule is simple: Hyphens are dropped, and a letter that follows a hyphen is translated to its upper-case (actually "title-case") equivalent. Otherwise, letters are translated as is.

Some special characters are handled specially. A final ‘?’ is replaced by an initial ‘is’, with the following letter converted to titlecase. Thus ‘number?’ is converted to ‘isNumber’ (which fits with Java conventions), and ‘file-exists?’ is converted to ‘isFileExists’ (which doesn’t really). The pair ‘->’ is translated to ‘$To$’. For example ‘list->string’ is translated to ‘list$To$string’.

Some symbols are mapped to a mnemonic sequence, starting with a dollar-sign, followed by a two-character abbreviation. For example, the less-than symbol ‘<’ is mangled as ‘$Ls’. See the source code to the mangleName method in the gnu.expr.Mangling class for the full list. Characters that do not have a mnemonic abbreviation are mangled as ‘$’ followed by a four-hex-digit unicode value. For example ‘Tamil vowel sign ai’ is mangled as ‘$0bc8’.

Note that this mapping may map different Scheme names to the same Java name. For example ‘string?’, ‘String?’, ‘is-string’, ‘is-String’, and ‘isString’ are all mapped to the same Java identifier ‘isString’. Code that uses such "Java-clashing" names is not supported. There is very partial support for renaming names in the case of a clash, and there may be better support in the future. However, some of the nice features of Kawa depend on being able to map Scheme name to Java names naturally, so we urge you to not write code that "mixes" naming conventions by using (say) the names ‘open-file’ and ‘openFile’ to name two different objects.

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Accessing object fields

Next: Scheme types in Java

Calling Java methods from Scheme

You can call a Java method as if it were a Scheme procedure using various mechanisms.

Calling static methods using colon notation

The easiest way to invoke a static method is to use colon notation, specifically:

(class-expression:method-name argument ...)

The class-expression can be a class in the current lexical scope, such as a class defined using define-simple-class:

(define-simple-class MyClass ()
  ((add2 x y) allocation: 'static (+ x y)))
(MyClass:add2 3 4) ⇒ 7

Often class-expression is a fully-qualified class name:

(java.lang.Math:sqrt 9.0) ⇒ 3.0

This is only allowed when the name is of a class that exists and is accessible both at compile-time and run-time, and the name is not otherwise lexically bound.

You can also use a defined alias:

(define-alias jlMath java.lang.Math)
(jlMath:sqrt 16.0) ⇒ 4.0

You can even evaluate class-expression at run-time (in which case Kawa may have to use slower reflection):

(let ((math java.lang.Math)) math:sqrt 9.0) ⇒ 3.0

Here java.lang.Math evaluates to a java.lang.Class instance for the named class (like Java’s java.lang.Class.class, again assuming the class exists and is accessible both at compile-time and run-time, and the name is not otherwise lexically bound.

Calling instance methods using colon notation

The syntax is:

(instance:method-name argument ...)

This invokes the method named method-name with the evaluated instance as the target object and the evaluated arguments as the method arguments.

For example:

((list 9 8 7):toString) ⇒ "(9 8 7)"
([5 6 7]:get 2) ⇒ 7

This older syntax is also available:

(*:method-name instance argument ...)

For example:

(*:toString (list 9 8 7))

You can also name the class explicitly:

(class-expression:method-name instance argument ...)

For example:

(java.util.List:get [5 6 7] 2) ⇒ 7

Using an explicit class is like coercing the instance:

(*:method-name (as class-expression instance )argument ...)

Note that for some special values, including java.lang.Class instances, you can’t use the compact form of colon notation where the instance is before the comma:

(java.lang.Integer:getDeclaredField "MAX_VALUE") ⇒ error

This is because in this case we look for a static member of java.lang.Integer (at least as currently defined and implemented), while we want an instance member of java.lang.Class. In those cases you can use one of these alternative forms, which all return the same java.lang.reflect.Field result:

(*:getDeclaredField java.lang.Integer "MAX_VALUE")
(java.lang.Class:getDeclaredField java.lang.Integer "MAX_VALUE")
(invoke java.lang.Integer 'getDeclaredField "MAX_VALUE")

Method names

The method to invoke is selected using the specified method name and argments. If specified name is not a Java name, it is "mangled" (see Mangling) into a valid Java name. All accessible methods whose names match are considered. Methods that match after appending $V or $X or $V$X are also considered. A $V suffix matches a variable number of arguments: any excess arguments are collect into an gnu.lists.LList or a Java array (depending on the final parameter type). A $X specifies that the method expects an extra implicit CallContext parameter. In that case the method’s result is written to the CallContext, so the method result type must be void.

(Kawa may compile a procedure with a #!rest or keyword args whose name is fn to a method named fn$V. It adds an implicit parameter for the extra arguments. By default this extra extra parameter is a Scheme list. You can specify a Java array type instead, in which case the method is named fn without the $V, and instead it is marked as a Java-5 varargs method. The array element type must be compatible with all the extra arguments.)

Invoking a method with the invoke function

If you prefer, you can instead use the following functions. (There is also an older deprecated lower-level interface (see Low-level Method invocation.)

Procedure: invoke-static class name args ...

The class can be a java.lang.Class, a gnu.bytecode.ClassType, or a symbol or string that names a Java class. The name can be symbol or string that names one or more methods in the Java class.

Any accessible methods (static or instance) in the specified class (or its super-classes) that match "name" or "name$V" collectively form a generic procedure. When the procedure is applied to the argument list, the most specific applicable method is chosen depending on the argument list; that method is then called with the given arguments. Iff the method is an instance method, the first actual argument is used as the this argument. If there are no applicable methods (or no methods at all!), or there is no "best" method, WrongType is thrown.

An example:

(invoke-static java.lang.Thread 'sleep 100)

The behavior of interpreted code and compiled code is not identical, though you should get the same result either way unless you have designed the classes rather strangely. The details will be nailed down later, but the basic idea is that the compiler will "inline" the invoke-static call if it can pick a single "best" matching method.

Procedure: invoke object name args ...

The name can be <symbol> or <string> that names one or more methods in the Java class.

Any accessible methods (static or instance) in the specified class (or its super-classes) that match "name" or "name$V" collectively form a generic procedure. When the procedure is applied to the argument list, the most specific applicable method is chosen depending on the argument list; that method is then called with the given arguments. Iff the method is an instance method, the object is used as the this argument; otherwise object is prepended to the args list. If there are no applicable methods (or no methods at all!), or there is no "best" method, WrongType is thrown.

The behavior of interpreted code and compiled code is not indentical, though you should get the same result either way unless you have designed the classes rather strangely. The details will be nailed down later, but the basic idea is that the compiler will "inline" the invoke-static call if it can pick a single "best" matching method.

If the compiler cannot determine the method to call (assuming the method name is constant), the compiler has to generate code at run-time to find the correct method. This is much slower, so the compiler will print a warning. To avoid a waning, you can use a type declaration, or insert a cast:

(invoke (as java.util.Date my-date) 'setDate cur-date)

or

(let ((my-date ::java.util.Date (calculate-date))
      (cur-date ::int (get-cur-date)))
  (invoke my-date 'setDate cur-date))

Procedure: invoke-special class receiver-object name arg ...

The class can be a java.lang.Class, a gnu.bytecode.ClassType, or a symbol or string that names a Java class. The name can be symbol or string that names one or more methods in the Java class.

This procedure is very similar to invoke and invoke-static and invokes the specified method, ignoring any methods in subclasses that might overide it. One interesting use is to invoke a method in your super-class like the Java language super keyword.

Any methods in the specified class that match "name" or "name$V" collectively form a generic procedure. That generic procedure is then applied as in invoke using the receiver-object and the arguments (if any).

The compiler must be able to inline this procedure (because you cannot force a specific method to be called using reflection). Therefore the class and name must resolve at compile-time to a specific method.

(define-simple-class <MyClass> (<java.util.Date>)
  ((get-year) :: <int>
   (+ (invoke-special <java.util.Date> (this) 'get-year)) 1900)
  ((set-year (year :: <int>)) :: <void>
   (invoke-special <java.util.Date> (this) 'set-year (- year 1900))))

Procedure: class-methods class name

Return a generic function containing those methods of class that match the name name, in the sense of invoke-static. Same as:

(lambda args (apply invoke-static (cons class (cons name args))))

Some examples using these functions are ‘vectors.scm’ and ‘characters.scm’ the directory ‘kawa/lib’ in the Kawa sources.

Using a namespace prefix

This way of invoking a method is deprecated.

You can use define-namespace to define an alias for a Java class:

(define-namespace Int32 "class:java.lang.Integer")

In this example the name Int32 is a namespace alias for the namespace whose full name is "class:java.lang.Integer". The full name should be the 6 characters "class:" followed by the fully-qualified name of a Java class.

Instead of a vamespace-uri you can use a variable that names a class, usually of the form <classname>. The following is equivalent to the above:

(define-namespace Int32 <java.lang.Integer>)

However, there is one important difference: The <classname> is first searched in the lexical scope. It may resolve to a class defined in the current compilation unit (perhaps defined using define-simple-class), or imported from another module, or an alias (such as from define-alias). Only if <classname> is not found in the current scope is it tried as the class name classname.

You can name a method using a qualified name containing a colon. The part of the name before the colon is a namespace alias (in this case Int32), and the part of the name after the colon is the method name. For example:

(Int32:toHexString 255) ⇒ "ff"

This invokes the static method toHexString in the Java class java.lang.Integer, passing it the argument 255, and returning the String "ff".

The general syntax is

(prefix:method-name arg ...)

This invokes the method named method-name in the class corresponding to prefix, and the args are the method arguments.

You can use the method name new to construct new objects:

(Int32:new '|255|)

This is equivalent to the Java expression new Integer("255"). You can also write:

(Int32:new "255")

You can also call instance methods using a namespace prefix:

(Int32:doubleValue (Int32:new "00255"))

This returns the double value 255.0.

As a shorthand, you can use the name of a Java class instead of a namespace alias:

(java.lang.Integer:toHexString 255)
(java.lang.Object:toString some-value)

If Kawa sees a qualified name with a prefix that is not defined and that matches the name of a known class, then Kawa will automatically treat the prefix as a nickname for namespace uri like class:java.lang.Integer. Both conditions should be true at both compile-time and run-time. However, using an explicit define-namespace is recommended.

As a final shorthand you can use an identifier in handle brackets, such as an existing type alias like <list>. The following are all equivalent:

(<list>:list3 'a 'b 'c)

This is equivalent to:

(define-namespace prefix <list>
(prefix:list3 'a 'b 'c)

for some otherwise-unused prefix.

Calling static methods using colon notation
Calling instance methods using colon notation
Method names
Invoking a method with the invoke function
Using a namespace prefix

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Creating New Record Types On-the-fly

Next: Allocating objects

Modules and how they are compiled to classes

Modules provide a way to organize Scheme into reusable parts with explicitly defined interfaces to the rest of the program. A module is a set of definitions that the module exports, as well as some actions (expressions evaluated for their side effect). The top-level forms in a Scheme source file compile a module; the source file is the module source. When Kawa compiles the module source, the result is the module class. Each exported definition is translated to a public field in the module class.

Name visibility

The definitions that a module exports are accessible to other modules. These are the "public" definitions, to use Java terminology. By default, all the identifiers declared at the top-level of a module are exported, except those defined using define-private. (If compiling with the --main flag, then by default no identifiers are exported.) However, a major purpose of using modules is to control the set of names exported. One reason is to reduce the chance of accidental name conflicts between separately developed modules. An even more important reason is to enforce an interface: Client modules should only use the names that are part of a documented interface, and should not use internal implementation procedures (since those may change).

If there is a module-export (or export) declaration in the module, then only those names listed are exported. There can be more than one module-export, and they can be anywhere in the Scheme file. The recommended style has a single module-export near the beginning of the file.

Syntax: module-export export-spec*

Syntax: export export-spec*

The forms export and module-export are equivalent. (The older Kawa name is module-export; export comes from R7RS.) Either form specifies a list of identifiers which can be made visible to other libraries or programs.

export-spec ::= identifier
  | (rename identifier1 identifier2)

In the former variant, an identifier names a single binding defined within or imported into the library, where the external name for the export is the same as the name of the binding within the library. A rename spec exports the binding defined within or imported into the library and named by identifier1, using identifier2 as the external name.

Note that it is an error if there is no definition for identifier (or identifier1) in the current module, or if it is defined using define-private.

As a matter of style, export or module-export should appear after module-name but before other commands (including import or require). (This is a requirement if there are any cycles.)

In this module, fact is public and worker is private:

(module-export fact)
(define (worker x) ...)
(define (fact x) ...)

Alternatively, you can write:

(define-private (worker x) ...)
(define (fact x) ...)

R7RS explicit library modules

A R7RS define-library form is another way to create a module. The R7RS term library is roughly the same as a Kawa module. In Kawa, each source file is a implicit module, which may contain zero or more explicit sub-modules (in the form of define-library) optionally followed by the definitions and expressions of the implicit (file-level) module.

Syntax: define-library library-name library-declaration*

library-name ::= ( library-name-parts )
library-name-parts ::= identifier+

A library-name is a list whose members are identifiers and exact non-negative integers. It is used to identify the library uniquely when importing from other programs or libraries. Libraries whose first identifier is scheme are reserved for use by the R7RS report and future versions of that report. Libraries whose first identifier is srfi are reserved for libraries implementing Scheme Requests for Implementation. It is inadvisable, but not an error, for identifiers in library names to contain any of the characters | \ ? * < " : > + [ ] / . or control characters after escapes are expanded.

See module-name for how a library-name is mapped to a class name.

library-declaration ::=
  export-declaration
  | import-declaration
  | (begin statement* )
  | (include filename+)
  | (include-ci filename+)
  | (include-library-declarations filename+)
  | (cond-expand cond-expand-clause* [(else command-or-definition*)])
  | statement

The begin, include, and include-ci declarations are used to specify the body of the library. They have the same syntax and semantics as the corresponding expression types. This form of begin is analogous to, but not the same as regular begin. A plain statement (which is allowed as a Kawa extension) is also part of the body of the library, as if it were wrapped in a begin).

The include-library-declarations declaration is similar to include except that the contents of the file are spliced directly into the current library definition. This can be used, for example, to share the same export declaration among multiple libraries as a simple form of library interface.

The cond-expand declaration has the same syntax and semantics as the cond-expand expression type, except that it expands to spliced-in library declarations rather than expressions enclosed in begin.

When a library is loaded, its expressions are executed in textual order. If a library’s definitions are referenced in the expanded form of a program or library body, then that library must be loaded before the expanded program or library body is evaluated. This rule applies transitively. If a library is imported by more than one program or library, it may possibly be loaded additional times.

Similarly, during the expansion of a library (foo), if any syntax keywords imported from another library (bar) are needed to expand the library, then the library (bar) must be expanded and its syntax definitions evaluated before the expansion of (foo).

Regardless of the number of times that a library is loaded, each program or library that imports bindings from a library must do so from a single loading of that library, regardless of the number of import declarations in which it appears. That is, (import (only (foo) a)) followed by (import (only (foo) b)) has the same effect as (import (only (foo) a b)).

How a module becomes a class

If you want to just use a Scheme module as a module (i.e. load or require it), you don’t care how it gets translated into a module class. However, Kawa gives you some control over how this is done, and you can use a Scheme module to define a class which you can use with other Java classes. This style of class definition is an alternative to define-class, which lets you define classes and instances fairly conveniently.

The default name of the module class is the main part of the filename of the Scheme source file (with directories and extensions stripped off). That can be overridden by the -T Kawa command-line flag. The package-prefix specified by the -P flag is prepended to give the fully-qualified class name.

Syntax: module-name name

Syntax: module-name <name>

Syntax: module-name library-name

Sets the name of the generated class, overriding the default. If there is no ‘.’ in the name, the package-prefix (specified by the -P Kawa command-line flag) is prepended.

If the form library-name is used, then the class name is the result of taking each identifier in the library-name-parts, mangling if needed, and concatenating them separated by periods. For example (org example doc-utils) becomes org.example.doc-utils. (You can’t reference the class name doc-utils directly in Java, but the JVM has no problems with it. In Java you can use reflection to access classes with such names.)

As a matter of style, module-name should be the first command in a file (after possible comments). It must appear before a require or import, in case of cycles.

By default, the base class of the generated module class is unspecified; you cannot count on it being more specific than Object. However, you can override it with module-extends.

Syntax: module-extends class

Specifies that the class generated from the immediately surrounding module should extend (be a sub-class of) the class class.

Syntax: module-implements interface ...

Specifies that the class generated from the immediately surrounding module should implement the interfaces listed.

Note that the compiler does not currently check that all the abstract methods requires by the base class or implemented interfaces are actually provided, and have the correct signatures. This will hopefully be fixed, but for now, if you are forgot a method, you will probably get a verifier error

For each top-level exported definition the compiler creates a corresponding public field with a similar (mangled) name. By default, there is some indirection: The value of the Scheme variable is not that of the field itself. Instead, the field is a gnu.mapping.Location object, and the value Scheme variable is defined to be the value stored in the Location. Howewer, if you specify an explicit type, then the field will have the specified type, instead of being a Location. The indirection using Location is also avoided if you use define-constant.

If the Scheme definition defines a procedure (which is not re-assigned in the module), then the compiler assumes the variable as bound as a constant procedure. The compiler generates one or more methods corresponding to the body of the Scheme procedure. It also generates a public field with the same name; the value of the field is an instance of a subclass of <gnu.mapping.Procedure> which when applied will execute the correct method (depending on the actual arguments). The field is used when the procedure used as a value (such as being passed as an argument to map), but when the compiler is able to do so, it will generate code to call the correct method directly.

You can control the signature of the generated method by declaring the parameter types and the return type of the method. See the applet (see Applet compilation) example for how this can be done. If the procedures has optional parameters, then the compiler will generate multiple methods, one for each argument list length. (In rare cases the default expression may be such that this is not possible, in which case an "variable argument list" method is generated instead. This only happens when there is a nested scope inside the default expression, which is very contrived.) If there are #!keyword or #!rest arguments, the compiler generate a "variable argument list" method. This is a method whose last parameter is either an array or a <list>, and whose name has $V appended to indicate the last parameter is a list.

Top-leval macros (defined using either define-syntax or defmacro) create a field whose type is currently a sub-class of kawa.lang.Syntax; this allows importing modules to detect that the field is a macro and apply the macro at compile time.

Unfortunately, the Java class verifier does not allow fields to have arbitrary names. Therefore, the name of a field that represents a Scheme variable is "mangled" (see Mangling) into an acceptable Java name. The implementation can recover the original name of a field X as ((gnu.mapping.Named) X).getName() because all the standard compiler-generated field types implement the Named interface.

Same class for module and defined class

You can declare a class using define-simple-class with the same name as the module class, for example the following in a file named foo.scm:

(define-simple-class foo ...)

In this case the defined class will serve dual-purpose as the module class.

To avoid confusion, in this case you must not specify module-extends, module-implements, or (module-static #t). Also, the defined class should not have public static members. In that case it works out pretty well: public static members represent bindings exported by the module; other non-private members “belong” to the defined class.

In this case (module-static 'init-run) is implied.

Static vs non-static modules

There are two kinds of module class: A static module is a class (or gets compiled to a class) all of whose public fields are static, and that does not have a public constructor. A JVM can only have a single global instance of a static module. An instance module has a public default constructor, and usually has at least one non-static public field. There can be multiple instances of an instance module; each instance is called a module instance. However, only a single instance of a module can be registered in an environment, so in most cases there is only a single instance of instance modules. Registering an instance in an environment means creating a binding mapping a magic name (derived from the class name) to the instance.

In fact, any Java class class that has the properties of either an instance module or a static module, is a module, and can be loaded or imported as such; the class need not have written using Scheme.

You can control whether a module is compiled to a static or a non-static class using either a command-line flag to the compiler, or using the module-static special form.

--module-static

Generate a static module (as if (module-static #t) were specified). This is (now) the default.

--module-nonstatic
--no-module-static

Generate a non-static module (as if (module-static #f) were specified). This used to be the default.

--module-static-run

Generate a static module (as if (module-static 'init-run) were specified).

Syntax: module-static name ...

Syntax: module-static #t

Syntax: module-static #f

Syntax: module-static 'init-run

Control whether the generated fields and methods are static. If #t or 'init-run is specified, then the module will be a static module, all definitions will be static. If 'init-run is specified, in addition the module body is evaluated in the class’s static initializer. (Otherwise, it is run the first time it is require’d.) Otherwise, the module is an instance module. If there is a non-empty list of names then the module is an instance module, but the names that are explicitly listed will be compiled to static fields and methods. If #f is specified, then all exported names will be compiled to non-static (instance) fields and methods.

By default, if no module-static is specified:

If there is a module-extends or module-implements declaration, or one of the --applet or --servlet command-line flags was specified, then (module-static #f) is implied.

If one of the command-line flags --no-module-static, --module-nonstatic, --module-static, or --module-static-run was specified, then the default is #f, #f, #t, or 'init-run, respectively.

If the module class is dual-purpose then (module-static 'init-run) is implied.

Otherwise the default is (module-static #t). (It used to be (module-static #f) in older Kawa versions.)

The default is (module-static #t). It usually produces more efficient code, and is recommended if a module contains only procedure or macro definitions. However, a static module means that all environments in a JVM share the same bindings, which you may not want if you use multiple top-level environments.

The top-level actions of a module will get compiled to a run method. If there is an explicit method-extends, then the module class will also automatically implement java.lang.Runnable. (Otherwise, the class does not implement Runnable, since in that case the run method return an Object rather than void. This will likely change.)

Module options

Certain compilation options can be be specified either on the command-line when compiling, or in the module itself.

Syntax: module-compile-options [key: value] ...

This sets the value of the key option to value for the current module (source file). It takes effect as soon it is seen during the first macro-expansion pass, and is active thereafter (unless overridden by with-compile-options).

The key: is one of the supported option names (The ending colon makes it a Kawa keyword). Valid option keys are:

main: - Generate an application, with a main method.

full-tailcalls: - Use a calling convention that supports proper tail recursion.

warn-undefined-variable: - Warn if no compiler-visible binding for a variable.

warn-unknown-member: - Warn if referencing an unknown method or field.

warn-invoke-unknown-method: - Warn if invoke calls an unknown method (subsumed by warn-unknown-member).

warn-unused: - Warn if a variable is usused or code never executed.

warn-unreachable: - Warn if this code can never be executed.

warn-void-used: - Warn if an expression depends on the value of a void sub-expression (one that never returns a value).

warn-as-error: - Treat a compilation warning as if it were an error.

The value must be a literal value: either a boolean (#t or #f), a number, or a string, depending on the key. (All the options so far are boolean options.)

(module-compile-options warn-undefined-variable: #t)
;; This causes a warning message that y is unknown.
(define (func x) (list x y))

Syntax: with-compile-options [key: value] ... body

Similar to module-compile-options, but the option is only active within body.

The module option key main: has no effect when applied to a particular body via the with-compile-options syntax.

(define (func x)
  (with-compile-options warn-invoke-unknown-method: #f
    (invoke x 'size)))

Name visibility
R7RS explicit library modules
How a module becomes a class
Same class for module and defined class
Static vs non-static modules
Module options

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Annotations of declarations

Next: Importing from a library

Namespaces and compound symbols

Different applications may want to use the same symbol to mean different things. To avoid such name clashes we can use compound symbols, which have two string parts: a local name and a namespace URI. The namespace-uri can be any string, but it is recommended that it have the form of an absolute URI. It would be too verbose to write the full URI all the time, so one usually uses a namespace prefix (namespace alias) as a short local alias to refer to a namespace URI.

Compound symbols are usually written using the infix colon operator:

prefix:local-name

where prefix is a namespace alias bound to some (lexically-known) namespace URI.

Compound symbols are used for namespace-aware XML processing.

Namespace objects

A namespace is a mapping from strings to symbols. The string is the local-name of the resulting symbol. A namespace is similar to a Common Lisp package.

A namespace has a namespace-uri, which a string; it is recommended that it have the form of an absolute URI. A namespace may optionally have a prefix, which is a string used when printing out symbols belonging to the namespace. (If you want “equivalent symbols” (i.e. those that have the same local-name and same uri) to be the identical symbol object, then you should use namespaces whose prefix is the empty string.)

Constructor: namespace name [prefix]

Return a namespace with the given name and prefix. If no such namespace exists, create it. The namespace-name is commonly a URI, especially when working with XML, in which case it is called a namespace-uri. However, any non-empty string is allowed. The prefix can be a string or a simple symbol. (If a symbol is used, then the symbol’s local-name is used.) The default for prefix is the empty string. Multiple calls with the same arguments will yield the same namespace object.

The reader macro #,namespace is equivalent to the namespace function, but it is invoked at read-time:

#,(namespace "http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xsl)
(eq? #,(namespace "foo") (namespace "foo")) ⇒ #t

The form (,#namespace "" "") returns the default empty namespace, which is used for simple symbols.

Procedure: namespace-uri namespace

Return the namespace-uri of the argument namespace, as a string.

Procedure: namespace-prefix namespace

Return the namespace prefix of the argument namespace, as a string.

Compound symbols

A compound symbol is one that belongs to a namespace other than the default empty namespace, and (normally) has a non-empty namespace uri. (It is possible for a symbol to belong to a non-default namespace and have an empty namespace uri, but that is not recommended.)

Constructor: symbol local-name namespace-spec

Constructor: symbol local-name [uri [prefix]]

Construct a symbol with the given local-name and namespace. If namespace-spec is a namespace object, then find (or, if needed, construct) a symbol with the given local-name belonging to the namespace. Multiple calls to symbol with the same namespace and local-name will yield the same symbol object.

If uri is a string (optionally followed by a prefix), then:

(symbol lname uri [prefix])

is equivalent to:

(symbol lname (namespace uri [prefix]))

Using #t for the namespace-spec is equivalent to using the empty namespace #,(namespace "").

Using #!null or #f for the namespace-spec creates an uninterned symbol, which does not belong to any namespace.

Procedure: symbol-local-name symbol

Return the local name of the argument symbol, as an immutable string. (The string is interned, except in the case of an uninterned symbol.)

Procedure: symbol-prefix symbol

Return the prefix of the argument symbol, as an immutable (and interned) string.

Procedure: symbol-namespace-uri symbol

Return the namespace uri of the argument symbol, as an immutable (and interned) string.

Procedure: symbol-namespace symbol

Return the namespace object (if any) of the argument symbol. Returns #!null if the symbol is uninterned.

Procedure: symbol=? symbol1 symbol2 symbol3 …

Return #t if the symbols are equivalent as symbols, i.e., if their local-names and namespace-uris are the same. They may have different values of symbol-prefix and symbol-namespace. If a symbol is uninterned (or is #!null) then symbol=? returns the same result as eq?.

Two symbols are equal? or eqv? if they’re symbol=?.

Namespace aliases

A namespace is usually referenced using a shorter namespace alias, which is is a lexical definition that binds a namespace prefix to a namespace object (and thus a namespace uri). This allows using compound symbols as identifiers in Scheme programs.

Syntax: define-namespace name namespace-name

Defines name as a namespace prefix - a lexically scoped "nickname" for the namespace whose full name is namespace-name, which should be a non-empty string literal. It is customary for the string have syntactic form of an absolute URI, but any non-empty string is acceptable and is used without further interpretation.

Any symbols in the scope of this definitions that contain a colon, and where the part before the colon matches the name will be treated as being in the package/namespace whose global unique name is the namespace-name.

Has mostly the same effect as:

(define-constant name #,(namespace namespace-name)

However, using define-namespace (rather than define-constant) is recommended if you want to use compound symbols as names of variables, especially local variables, or if you want to quote compound symbols.

Note that the prefix is only visible lexically: it is not part of the namespace, or thus indirectly the symbols, and so is not available when printing the symbol. You might consider using define-xml-namespace as an alternative.

A namespace is similar to a Common Lisp package, and the namespace-name is like the name of the package. However, a namespace alias belongs to the lexical scope, while a Common Lisp package nickname is global and belongs to the package itself.

If the namespace-name starts with the string "class:", then the name can be used for invoking Java methods (see Method operations) and accessing fields (see Field operations).

You can use a namespace as an abbreviation or renaming of a class name, but as a matter of style define-alias is preferred.

Syntax: define-private-namespace name namespace-name

Same as define-namespace, but the prefix name is local to the current module.

For example, you might have a set of a geometry definitions defined under the namespace-uri "http://foo.org/lib/geometry":

(define-namespace geom "http://foo.org/lib/geometry")
(define (geom:translate x y)
  (java.awt.geom.AffineTransform:getTranslateInstance x y))
(define geom:zero (geom:translate 0 0))
geom:zero
  ⇒ AffineTransform[[1.0, 0.0, 0.0], [0.0, 1.0, 0.0]]

You could have some other definitions for complex math:

(define-namespace complex "http://foo.org/lib/math/complex")
(define complex:zero +0+0i)

You can use a namespace-value directly in a compound name:

(namespace "http://foo.org/lib/geometry"):zero
  ⇒ AffineTransform[[1.0, 0.0, 0.0], [0.0, 1.0, 0.0]]

The variation define-xml-namespace is used for Creating XML nodes.

Syntax: define-xml-namespace prefix "namespace-uri"

Defines a namespace with prefix prefix and URI namespace-uri. This is similar to define-namespace but with two important differences:

Every symbol in the namespace automatically maps to an element-constructor-type, as with the html namespace.

The prefix is a component of the namespace object, and hence indirectly of any symbols belongining to the namespace.

Thus the definition is roughly equivalent to:

(define-constant name #,(namespace namespace-name name)

along with an infinite set of definitions, for every possible tag:

(define (name:tag . rest) (apply make-element 'name:tag rest))

$ kawa --output-format xml
#|kawa:1|# (define-xml-namespace na "Namespace1")
#|kawa:2|# (define-xml-namespace nb "Namespace1")
#|kawa:3|# (define xa (na:em "Info"))
#|kawa:4|# xa
<na:em xmlns:na="Namespace1">Info</na:em>
#|kawa:5|# (define xb (nb:em "Info"))
#|kawa:6|# xa
<nb:em xmlns:nb="Namespace1">Info</nb:em>

Note that the prefix is part of the qualified name (it is actually part of the namespace object), and it is used when printing the tag. Two qualified names (symbols) that have the same local-name and the same namespace-name are considered equal, even if they have different prefix. You can think of the prefix as annotation used when printing, but not otherwise part of the “meaning” of a compound symbol. They are the same object if they also have the same prefix. This is an important difference from traditional Lisp/Scheme symbols, but it is how XML QNames work.

#|kawa:7|# (instance? xb na:em)
true
#|kawa:8|# (eq? 'na:em 'nb:em)
false
#|kawa:9|# (equal? 'na:em 'nb:em)
true
#|kawa:10|# (eqv? 'na:em 'nb:em)
true

(Note that #t is printed as true when using XML formatting.)

The predefined html prefix could be defined thus:

(define-xml-namespace html "http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml")

Namespace objects
Compound symbols
Namespace aliases

Up: Symbols and namespaces

Previous: Simple symbols

Next: Keywords

Numerical types

Mathematically, numbers are arranged into a tower of subtypes in which each level is a subset of the level before it: number; complex number; real number; rational number; integer.

For example, 3 is an integer. Therefore 3 is also a rational, a real, and a complex number. The same is true of the Scheme numbers that model 3. For Scheme numbers, these types are defined by the predicates number?, complex?, real?, rational?, and integer?.

There is no simple relationship between a number’s type and its representation inside a computer. Although most implementations of Scheme will offer at least two different representations of 3, these different representations denote the same integer.

Scheme’s numerical operations treat numbers as abstract data, as independent of their representation as possible. Although an implementation of Scheme may use multiple internal representations of numbers, this ought not to be apparent to a casual programmer writing simple programs.

Type: number

The type of Scheme numbers.

Type: quantity

The type of quantities optionally with units. This is a sub-type of number.

Type: complex

The type of complex numbers. This is a sub-type of quantity.

Type: real

The type of real numbers. This is a sub-type of complex.

Type: rational

The type of exact rational numbers. This is a sub-type of real.

Type: integer

The type of exact Scheme integers. This is a sub-type of rational.

Kawa allows working with expressions of “primitive” types, which are supported by the JVM without object allocation, and using builtin arithmetic. Using these types may be much faster, assuming the compiler is able to infer that the variable or expression has primitive type.

Type: long

Type: int

Type: short

Type: byte

These are fixed-sized primitive signed exact integer types, of respectively 64, 32, 18, and 8 bits. If a value of one of these types needs to be converted to an object, the standard classes java.lang.Long, java.lang.Integer, java.lang.Short, or java.lang.Byte, respectively, are used.

Type: ulong

Type: uint

Type: ushort

Type: ubyte

These are fixed-sized primitive unsigned exact integer types, of respectively 64, 32, 18, and 8 bits. These are presented at runtime using the corresponding signed types (long, int, short, or byte). However, for arithmetic the Kawa compiler generates code to perform the “mathematically correct” result, truncated to an unsigned result rather than signed. If a value of one of these types needs to be converted to an object, the classes gnu.math.ULong, gnu.math.UInt, gnu.math.UShort, or gnu.math.UByte is used.

Type: double

Type: float

These are fixed-size primitive inexact floating-point real types, using the standard 64-bit or 32-bit IEEE representation. If a value of one of these types needs to be converted to an object, the standard classes java.lang.Double, or java.lang.Float is used.

Exactness

It is useful to distinguish between numbers that are represented exactly and those that might not be. For example, indexes into data structures must be known exactly, as must some polynomial coefficients in a symbolic algebra system. On the other hand, the results of measurements are inherently inexact, and irrational numbers may be approximated by rational and therefore inexact approximations. In order to catch uses of inexact numbers where exact numbers are required, Scheme explicitly distinguishes exact from inexact numbers. This distinction is orthogonal to the dimension of type.

A Scheme number is exact if it was written as an exact constant or was derived from exact numbers using only exact operations. A number is inexact if it was written as an inexact constant, if it was derived using inexact ingredients, or if it was derived using inexact operations. Thus inexactness is a contagious property of a number. In particular, an exact complex number has an exact real part and an exact imaginary part; all other complex numbers are inexact complex numbers.

If two implementations produce exact results for a computation that did not involve inexact intermediate results, the two ultimate results will be mathematically equal. This is generally not true of computations involving inexact numbers since approximate methods such as floating-point arithmetic may be used, but it is the duty of the implementation to make the result as close as practical to the mathematically ideal result.

Rational operations such as + should always produce exact results when given exact arguments. If the operation is unable to produce an exact result, then it may either report the violation of an implementation restriction or it may silently coerce its result to an inexact value.

Except for exact, the operations described in this section must generally return inexact results when given any inexact arguments. An operation may, however, return an exact result if it can prove that the value of the result is unaffected by the inexactness of its arguments. For example, multiplication of any number by an exact zero may produce an exact zero result, even if the other argument is inexact.

Specifically, the expression (* 0 +inf.0) may return 0, or +nan.0, or report that inexact numbers are not supported, or report that non-rational real numbers are not supported, or fail silently or noisily in other implementation-specific ways.

The procedures listed below will always return exact integer results provided all their arguments are exact integers and the mathematically expected results are representable as exact integers within the implementation: -, *, +, abs, ceiling, denominator, exact-integer-sqrt, expt, floor, floor/, floor-quotient, floor-remainder, gcd, lcm, max, min, modulo, numerator, quotient, rationalize, remainder, square, truncate, truncate/, truncate-quotient, truncate-remainder.

Numerical promotion and conversion

When combining two values of different numeric types, the values are converted to the first line in the following that subsumes (follows) both types. The computation is done using values of that type, and so is the result. For example adding a long and a float converts the former to the latter, yielding a float.

Note that short, byte, ushort, ubyte are converted to int regardless, even in the case of a single-operand operation, such as unary negation. Another exception is trancendental functions (such as cos), where integer operands are converted to double.

int subsumes short, byte, ushort, ubyte.

uint

long

ulong

java.lang.BigInteger

integer (i.e. gnu.math.IntNum)

rational (i.e. gnu.math.RatNum)

float

double

gnu.math.FloNum

real (i.e. gnu.math.RealNum)

number

complex

quantity

When comparing a primitive signed integer value with a primitive unsigned integer (for example < applied to a int and a ulong) the mathemically correct result is computed, as it converting both operands to integer.

Exactness
Numerical promotion and conversion

Up: Quantities and Numbers

Next: Arithmetic operations

Command-line arguments

You can pass various flags to Kawa, for example:

kawa -e '(display (+ 12 4))(newline)'

or:

java kawa.repl -e '(display (+ 12 4))(newline)'

Either causes Kawa to print ‘16’, and then exit.

At startup, Kawa executes an init file from the user’s home directory. The init file is named .kawarc.scm on Unix-like systems (those for which the file separator is '/'), and kawarc.scm on other systems. This is done before the read-eval-print loop or before the first -f or -c argument. (It is not run for a -e command, to allow you to set options to override the defaults.)

Argument processing

Kawa processes the command-line arguments in order. Options (which either start with ‘-’ or contain a ‘=’) may “use up” one or more command arguments. Some of the options (‘-c’, ‘-e’, ‘-f’, ‘-s’, ‘-C’, -w, ‘--’, --browse-manual) are action options; others set various properties.

When all the command-line arguments have been “used up” and if no action options have been seen, then Kawa enters an interactive read-eval-print loop. (If an action option has been seen, we’re done.)

If the next command-line argument is not an option (does not start with ‘-’ nor contains a ‘=’) then we’re done if we’ve seen an action option (and the last action option wasn’t preceded by --with-arg-count). (Presumably any remaining arguments were command-line-arguments used by the action option.)

Otherwise, the first remaining argument names either a file that is read and evaluated, or a compiled class. In the former case, the whole file is read and compiled as a module before being loaded (unlike the -f flag which reads and evaluates the file command by command.) If the argument is the fully-qualified name of a class, then the class is loaded, an instance allocated, and its run method invoked. If the class was compiled from a Kawa Scheme module, then invoking run has the effect of evaluating the module body. The command-line-arguments vector is set to any remaining arguments after the file/class name. (This can be overridden with the --with-arg-count option. Command-line processing continues if there are any further arguments.)

General options

-e expr

Kawa evaluates expr, which contains one or more Scheme expressions. Does not cause the ~/.kawarc.scm init file to be run.

-c expr

Same as ‘-e expr’, except that it does cause the ~/.kawarc.scm init file to be run.

-f filename-or-url

Kawa reads and evaluates expressions from the file named by filename-or-url. If the latter is ‘-’, standard input is read (with no prompting). Otherwise, it is equivalent to evaluating ‘(load "filename-or-url")’. The filename-or-url is interpreted as a URL if it is absolute - it starts with a "URI scheme" like http:.

-s
--

The remaining arguments (if any) are passed to ‘command-line-arguments’ and (the cdr of) (command-line), and an interactive read-eval-print loop is started. This uses the same "console" as where you started up Kawa; use ‘-w’ to get a new window.

--script filename-or-url
--scriptN filename-or-url

The global variable ‘command-line-arguments’ is set to the remaining arguments (if any). Kawa reads and evaluates expressions from the file named by filename-or-url. If script is followed by an integer N, then N lines are skipped first.

Skipping some initial lines is useful if you want to have a non-Kawa preamble before the actual Kawa code. One use for this is for Kawa shell scripts (see Scripts).

-w
-wsub-option

Creates a new top-level window, and runs an interactive read-eval-print in the new window. See New-Window. Same as -e (scheme-window #t). You can specify multiple ‘-w’ options, and also use ‘-s’.

--help

Prints out some help.

--version

Prints out the Kawa version number, and then exits.

If Kawa was built with a .git repository present, also prints the result of git describe.

--browse-manual
--browse-manual=command

Browse a local copy of the documentation (this manual).

This creates a mini web-server that reads from doc/kawa-manual.epub, which is included in the binary distributions, but not built by default from source.

If no command is specified, creates a new window or tab in your default web browser. If command is a string containing %U, then Kawa replaces %U with a URL that references itself, and then executes the resulting command. If command does not contain %U, then command becomes command" %U". For example to use the Firefox browser to browse the manual do either of:

kawa --browse-manual=firefox
kawa --browse-manual="firefox %U"

--server portnum

Start a server listening from connections on the specified portnum. Each connection using the Telnet protocol causes a new read-eval-print-loop to start. This option allows you to connect using any Telnet client program to a remote "Kawa server".

--with-arg-count=argc

This option is used before an action option (such as -f). The argc arguments after the action become the value of the command-line-arguments during the action. When the action is finished, command-line-processing resumes after skipping the argc arguments.

For example:

$ kawa -f a.scm -f b.scm x y

When evaluating a.scm the command-line-arguments by default is all the remaining arguments: ["-f" "b.scm" "x" "y"]. Then b.scm is evaluated with command-line-arguments set to ["x" "y"]

$ kawa --with-arg-count=0 -f a.scm -f b.scm x y

In this case a.scm is evaluated with command-line-arguments set to the empty vector [], and then b.scm is evaluated with command-line-arguments set to ["x" "y"]

$ kawa --with-arg-count=4 -f a.scm -f b.scm x y

In this case a.scm is evaluated with command-line-arguments set to ["-f" "b.scm" "x" "y"]. Since command-line processing skips the arguments specified by --with-arg-count=4, in this case b.scm is not evaluated.

Options for language selection

--scheme

Set the default language to Scheme. (This is the default unless you select another language, or you name a file with a known extension on the command-line.)

--r5rs
--r6rs
--r7rs

Provide better compatibility with the specified Scheme standards. (This is a work-in-progress.) For example --r6rs aims to disable Kawa extensions that conflict with R6RS. It does not aim to disable all extensions, only incompatible extensions. These extensions disable the colon operator and keyword literals, as well as the use of initial ‘@’ as a splicing operator. The “l” exponent suffix of a number literal creates a floating-point double, rather than a BigInteger. Selecting --r5rs makes symbols by default case-insensitive.

--elisp
--emacs
--emacs-lisp

Set the default language to Emacs Lisp. (The implementation is quite incomplete.)

--lisp
--clisp
--clisp
--commonlisp
--common-lisp

Set the default language to CommonLisp. (The implementation is very incomplete.)

--krl

Set the default language to KRL. See KRL.

--brl

Set the default language to KRL, in BRL-compatibility mode. See KRL.

--xquery

Set the default language to the draft XML Query language. See the Kawa-XQuery page for more information.

--xslt

Set the default language to XSLT (XML Stylesheet Language Transformations). (The implementation is very incomplete.) See the Kawa-XSLT page for more information.

--pedantic

Try to follow the approprate language specification to the letter, even in corner cases, and even if it means giving up some Kawa convenience features. This flag so far only affects the XQuery parser, but that will hopefully change.

Options for warnings and errors

--warn-undefined-variable

Emit a warning if the code references a variable which is neither in lexical scope nor in the compile-time dynamic (global) environment. This is useful for catching typos. (A define-variable form can be used to silence warnings. It declares to the compiler that a variable is to be resolved dynamically.) This defaults to on; to turn it off use the --no-warn-undefined-variable flag.

--warn-unknown-member

Emit a warning if the code references a named member (field or method) for which there is no match in the compile-time type of the receiver. This defaults to on; to turn it off use the --no-warn-unknown-member flag.

--warn-invoke-unknown-method

Emit a warning if the invoke function calls a named method for which there is no matching method in the compile-time type of the receiver. This defaults to the value of --warn-unknown-member, to turn it off use the --no-warn-invoke-unknown-method flag.

--warn-unused

Emit a warning if a variable is unused or code never executed. This defaults to on; to turn it off use the --no-warn-unused flag.

--warn-unreachable

Emit a warning if the code can never be executed. This defaults to on; to turn it off use the --no-warn-unreachable flag.

--warn-void-used

Emit a warning if an expression depends on an expression that is void (always has zero values), including call to void functions and method. Also warn if an expression depends on a conditional (if) that has no “else” clause. Examples include using the value of set-car! as an argument to a function, or to initialize a variable. This defaults to on; to turn it off use the --no-warn-void-used flag.

--warn-as-error

Treat a compilation warning as if it were an error and halt compilation.

An option can be followed by a value, as in --warn-invoke-unknown-method=no. For boolean options, the values yes, true, on, or 1 enable the option, while no, false, off, or 0 disable it. You can also negate an option by prefixing it with no-: The option --no-warn-unknown-member is the same as --warn-unknown-member=no.

These options can also be used in the module source, using module-compile-options or with-compile-options. (In that case they override the options on the command line.)

Options for setting variables

name=value

Set the global variable with the specified name to the given value. The type of the value is currently unspecified; the plan is for it to be like XQuery’s untyped atomic which can be coerced as needed.

{namespace-uri}local-name=value

Set the global variable with the specified namespace uri and namespace-local name to the given value.

These options are processed when invoking the kawa application (i.e. the kawa.repl application). If you want a Kawa application compiled with --main to process these these assignments, call the process-command-line-assignments utility function.

-Dvariable-name=variable-value

Sets the JVM property variable-name to variable-value, using the setProperty method of java.lang.System.

Options for the REPL console

--console
--no-console

Usually Kawa can detect when the standard input port is a “console” or “terminal”, but these are useful for overriding that detection. The --console flag is useful when the standard input is a pipe, but you want to direct Kawa to treat it as an interactive terminal. The --no-console flag was useful for older pre-Java-6 implementations that did not have the java.lang.Console class.

console:type=console-types
console:use-jline=[yes|no]
console:jline-mouse=[yes|no]

See the REPL Console section.

console:prompt1=prompt1
console:prompt2=prompt2

Initialize input-promp1 and input-prompt2, respectively.

See also the --output-format flag.

Options for controlling output formatting

--output-format format
--format format

Change the default output format to that specified by format. See Named output formats for more information and a list.

out:base=integer

The number base (radix) to use by default when printing rational numbers. Must be an integer between 2 and 36, and the default is of course 10. For example the option out:base=16 produces hexadecimal output. Equivalent to setting the *print-base* variable.

out:radix=no|yes

If true, prints an indicator of the radix used when printing rational numbers. The default is no. Equivalent to setting the *print-radix* variable.

out:doctype-system=system-identifier

If out:doctype-system is specified then a DOCTYPE declaration is written before writing a top-level XML element, using the specified system-identifier.

out:doctype-public=public-identifier

Ignored unless out:doctype-system is also specified, in which case the public-identifier is written as the public identifiers of the DOCTYPE declaration.

out:xml-indent=kind

Controls whether extra line breaks and indentation are added when printing XML. If kind is always or yes then newlines and appropriate indentation are added before and after each element. If kind is pretty then the pretty-printer is used to only add new lines when an element otherwise won’t fit on a single line. If kind is no (the default) then no extra line breaks or indentation are added.

out:line-length=columns
out:right-margin=columns

Specifies the maximum number of number of columns in a line when the pretty-printer decides where to break a line. (The two options are equivalent.)

Options for compiling and optimizing

--target version

The version can be a JDK or Java specification version: 5, 6, or 7. The JDK versions 1.5 and 1.6 are equivalent to 5 or 6, respectively. Specify a JVM (classfile) version to target. This is useful if (for example) you use Java 6, but want to create .class files that can run on Java 5. In that case specify --target 5.

The following options control which calling conventions are used:

--full-tailcalls

Use a calling convention that supports proper tail recursion.

--no-full-tailcalls

Use a calling convention that does not support proper tail recursion. Self-tail-recursion (i.e. a recursive call to the current function) is still implemented correctly, assuming that the called function is known at compile time.

--no-inline

Disable inlining of known functions and methods. The generated code runs slower, but you can more reliably trace procedures. Normally Kawa will assume that a procedure fn declared using a (define (fn args) body) form is constant, assuming it isn’t modified in the current module. However, it is possible some other module might modify the binding of fn. You can use the --no-inline to disable the assumption that fn is constant.

The default is currently --no-full-tailcalls because it is usually faster. It is also closer to the Java call model, so may be better for people primarily interested in using Kawa for scripting Java systems.

Both calling conventions can co-exist: Code compiled with --full-tailcalls can call code compiled with --no-full-tailcalls and vice versa.

These options can also be used in the module source, using module-compile-options or with-compile-options. (In that case they override the options on the command line.)

The options ‘-C’, ‘-d’, ‘-T’, ‘-P’, ‘--main’ ‘--applet’, and --servlet are used to compile a Scheme file; see Files compilation. The options ‘--module-static’, --module-nonstatic, --no-module-static, and --module-static-run control how a module is mapped to a Java class; see static-or-non-modules. The option ‘--connect portnum’ is only used by the ‘kawa’ front-end program.

Options for debugging

The following options are useful if you want to debug or understand how Kawa works.

--debug-dump-zip

Normally, when Kawa loads a source file, or evaluates a non-trivial expression, it generates new internal Java classes but does not write them out. This option asks it to write out generated classes in a ‘.zip’ archive whose name has the prefix ‘kawa-zip-dump-’.

--debug-print-expr

Kawa translates source language forms into an internal Expression data structure. This option causes that data structure to be written out in a readable format to the standard output.

--debug-print-final-expr

Similar to the previous option, but prints out the Expression after various transformations and optimizations have been done, and just before code generation.

--debug-syntax-pattern-match

Prints logging information to standard error when a syntax-rules or syntax-case pattern matches.

--debug-error-prints-stack-trace

Prints a stack trace with any error found during compilation.

--debug-warning-prints-stack-trace

Prints a stack trace with any warning found during compilation.

Options for web servers

JDK 6 (or later) includes a complete web server library.

--http-auto-handler context-path appdir

Register a web application handler that uses files in the directory appdir to handle HTTP (web) requests containing the given context-path. That is it handles requests that start with http://localhost:portcontext-path. (This assumes the context-path starts with a /.) See Self-configuring page scripts.

--http-start port

Start the web server, listing on the specified port.

Options for the JVM

The kawa front-end can pass options to the java launcher, using -J or -D options. These must be given before any other arguments. For example:

kawa -J-Xms48m -Dkawa.command.name=foo foo.scm

is equivalent to (ignoring classpath issues):

java -Xms48m -Dkawa.command.name=foo kawa.repl foo.scm

You can also pass a -D option (but not a -J option) after the class name, in which case it is processed by the Kawa command-line processor rather than the java launcher. The effect is normally the same.

-Jjvm-option

Passes the jvm-option to the java command, before the class-name (kawa.repl) and Kawa options.

-Dvariable-name=variable-value

Sets the JVM property variable-name to variable-value. Equivalent to -J-Dvariable-name=variable-value.

Argument processing
General options
Options for language selection
Options for warnings and errors
Options for setting variables
Options for the REPL console
Options for controlling output formatting
Options for compiling and optimizing
Options for debugging
Options for web servers
Options for the JVM

Up: How to start up and run Kawa

Next: Running Command Scripts

Ports

Ports represent input and output devices. An input port is a Scheme object that can deliver data upon command, while an output port is a Scheme object that can accept data.

Different port types operate on different data:

A textual port supports reading or writing of individual characters from or to a backing store containing characters using read-char and write-char below, and it supports operations defined in terms of characters, such as read and write.

A binary port supports reading or writing of individual bytes from or to a backing store containing bytes using read-u8 and write-u8 below, as well as operations defined in terms of bytes (integers in the range 0 to 255).

All Kawa binary ports created by procedures documented here are also textual ports. Thus you can either read/write bytes as described above, or read/write characters whose scalar value is in the range 0 to 255 (i.e. the Latin-1 character set), using read-char and write-char.

A native binary port is a java.io.InputStream or java.io.OutputStream instance. These are not textual ports. You can use methods read-u8 and write-u8, but not read-char and write-char on native binary ports. (The functions input-port?, output-port?, binary-port?, and port? all currently return false on native binary ports, but that may change.)

Procedure: call-with-port port proc

The call-with-port procedure calls proc with port as an argument. If proc returns, then the port is closed automatically and the values yielded by the proc are returned.

If proc does not return, then the port must not be closed automatically unless it is possible to prove that the port will never again be used for a read or write operation.

As a Kawa extension, port may be any object that implements java.io.Closeable. It is an error if proc does not accept one argument.

Procedure: call-with-input-file path proc

Procedure: call-with-output-file path proc

These procedures obtain a textual port obtained by opening the named file for input or output as if by open-input-file or open-output-file. The port and proc are then passed to a procedure equivalent to call-with-port.

It is an error if proc does not accept one argument.

Procedure: input-port? obj

Procedure: output-port? obj

Procedure: textual-port? obj

Procedure: binary-port? obj

Procedure: port? obj

These procedures return #t if obj is an input port, output port, textual port, binary port, or any kind of port, respectively. Otherwise they return #f.

These procedures currently return #f on a native Java streams (java.io.InputStream or java.io.OutputStream), a native reader (a java.io.Reader that is not an gnu.mapping.Inport), or a native writer (a java.io.Writer that is not an gnu.mapping.Outport). This may change if conversions between native ports and Scheme ports becomes more seamless.

Procedure: input-port-open? port

Procedure: output-port-open? port

Returns #t if port is still open and capable of performing input or output, respectively, and #f otherwise. (Not supported for native binary ports - i.e. java.io.InputStteam or java.io.OutputStream.)

Procedure: current-input-port

Procedure: current-output-port

Procedure: current-error-port

Returns the current default input port, output port, or error port (an output port), respectively. (The error port is the port to which errors and warnings should be sent - the standard error in Unix and C terminology.) These procedures are parameter objects, which can be overridden with parameterize.

The initial bindings for (current-output-port) and (current-error-port) are hybrid textual/binary ports that wrap the values of the corresponding java.lang.System fields out, and err. The latter, in turn are bound to the standard output and error streams of the JVM process. This means you can write binary data to standard output using write-bytevector and write-u8.

The initial value (current-input-port) similarly is a textual port that wraps the java.lang.System field in, which is bound to the standard input stream of the JVM process. It is a hybrid textual/binary port only if there is no console (as determined by (java.lang.System:console) returning #!null) - i.e. if standard input is not a tty.

Here is an example that copies standard input to standard output:

(let* ((in (current-input-port))
       (out (current-output-port))
       (blen ::int 2048)
       (buf (make-bytevector blen)))
  (let loop ()
    (define n (read-bytevector! buf in))
    (cond ((not (eof-object? n))
           (write-bytevector buf out 0 n)
           (loop)))))

Procedure: with-input-from-file path thunk

Procedure: with-output-to-file path thunk

The file is opened for input or output as if by open-input-file or open-output-file, and the new port is made to be the value returned by current-input-port or current-output-port (as used by (read), (write obj), and so forth). The thunk is then called with no arguments. When the thunk returns, the port is closed and the previous default is restored. It is an error if thunk does not accept zero arguments. Both procedures return the values yielded by thunk. If an escape procedure is used to escape from the continuation of these procedures, they behave exactly as if the current input or output port had been bound dynamically with parameterize.

Procedure: open-input-file path

Procedure: open-binary-input-file path

Takes a path naming an existing file and returns a textual input port or binary input port that is capable of delivering data from the file.

The procedure open-input-file checks the fluid variable port-char-encoding to determine how bytes are decoded into characters. The procedure open-binary-input-file is equivalent to calling open-input-file with port-char-encoding set to #f.

Procedure: open-output-file path

Procedure: open-binary-output-file path

Takes a path naming an output file to be created and returns respectively a textual output port or binary output port that is capable of writing data to a new file by that name. If a file with the given name already exists, the effect is unspecified.

The procedure open-output-file checks the fluid variable port-char-encoding to determine how characters are encoded as bytes. The procedure open-binary-output-file is equivalent to calling open-output-file with port-char-encoding set to #f.

Procedure: close-port port

Procedure: close-input-port port

Procedure: close-output-port port

Closes the resource associated with port, rendering the port incapable of delivering or accepting data. It is an error to apply the last two procedures to a port which is not an input or output port, respectively. (Specifically, close-input-port requires a java.io.Reader, while close-output-port requires a java.io.Writer. In contrast close-port accepts any object whose class implements java.io.Closeable.)

These routines have no effect if the port has already been closed.

String and bytevector ports

Procedure: open-input-string string

Takes a string and returns a text input port that delivers characters from the string. The port can be closed by close-input-port, though its storage will be reclaimed by the garbage collector if it becomes inaccessible.

(define p
  (open-input-string "(a . (b c . ())) 34"))

(input-port? p)                 ⇒  #t
(read p)                        ⇒  (a b c)
(read p)                        ⇒  34
(eof-object? (peek-char p))     ⇒  #t

Procedure: open-output-string

Returns an textual output port that will accumulate characters for retrieval by get-output-string. The port can be closed by the procedure close-output-port, though its storage will be reclaimed by the garbage collector if it becomes inaccessible.

(let ((q (open-output-string))
  (x '(a b c)))
    (write (car x) q)
    (write (cdr x) q)
    (get-output-string q))        ⇒  "a(b c)"

Procedure: get-output-string output-port

Given an output port created by open-output-string, returns a string consisting of the characters that have been output to the port so far in the order they were output. If the result string is modified, the effect is unspecified.

(parameterize
    ((current-output-port (open-output-string)))
    (display "piece")
    (display " by piece ")
    (display "by piece.")
    (newline)
    (get-output-string (current-output-port)))
        ⇒ "piece by piece by piece.\n"

Procedure: call-with-input-string string proc

Create an input port that gets its data from string, call proc with that port as its one argument, and return the result from the call of proc

Procedure: call-with-output-string proc

Create an output port that writes its data to a string, and call proc with that port as its one argument. Return a string consisting of the data written to the port.

Procedure: open-input-bytevector bytevector

Takes a bytevector and returns a binary input port that delivers bytes from the bytevector.

Procedure: open-output-bytevector

Returns a binary output port that will accumulate bytes for retrieval by get-output-bytevector.

Procedure: get-output-bytevector port

Returns a bytevector consisting of the bytes that have been output to the port so far in the order they were output. It is an error if port was not created with open-output-bytevector.

Input

If port is omitted from any input procedure, it defaults to the value returned by (current-input-port). It is an error to attempt an input operation on a closed port.

Procedure: read [port]

The read procedure converts external representations of Scheme objects into the objects themselves. That is, it is a parser for the non-terminal datum. It returns the next object parsable from the given textual input port, updating port to point to the first character past the end of the external representation of the object.

If an end of file is encountered in the input before any characters are found that can begin an object, then an end-of-file object is returned. The port remains open, and further attempts to read will also return an end-of-file object. If an end of file is encountered after the beginning of an object’s external representation, but the external representation is incomplete and therefore not parsable, an error that satisfies read-error? is signaled.

Procedure: read-char [port]

Returns the next character available from the textual input port, updating the port to point to the following character. If no more characters are available, an end-of-file value is returned.

The result type is character-or-eof.

Procedure: peek-char [port]

Returns the next character available from the textual input port, but without updating the port to point to the following character. If no more characters are available, an end-of-file value is returned.

The result type is character-or-eof.

Note: The value returned by a call to peek-char is the same as the value that would have been returned by a call to read-char with the same port. The only difference is that the very next call to read-char or peek-char on that port will return the value returned by the preceding call to peek-char. In particular, a call to peek-char on an interactive port will hang waiting for input whenever a call to read-char would have hung.

Procedure: read-line [port [handle-newline]]

Reads a line of input from the textual input port. The handle-newline parameter determines what is done with terminating end-of-line delimiter. The default, 'trim, ignores the delimiter; 'peek leaves the delimiter in the input stream; 'concat appends the delimiter to the returned value; and 'split returns the delimiter as a second value. You can use the last three options to tell if the string was terminated by end-or-line or by end-of-file. If an end of file is encountered before any end of line is read, but some characters have been read, a string containing those characters is returned. (In this case, 'trim, 'peek, and 'concat have the same result and effect. The 'split case returns two values: The characters read, and the delimiter is an empty string.) If an end of file is encountered before any characters are read, an end-of-file object is returned. For the purpose of this procedure, an end of line consists of either a linefeed character, a carriage return character, or a sequence of a carriage return character followed by a linefeed character.

Procedure: eof-object? obj

Returns #t if obj is an end-of-file object, otherwise returns #f.

Performance note: If obj has type character-or-eof, this is compiled as an int comparison with -1.

Procedure: eof-object

Returns an end-of-file object.

Procedure: char-ready? [port]

Returns #t if a character is ready on the textual input port and returns #f otherwise. If char-ready returns #t then the next read-char operation on the given port is guaranteed not to hang. If the port is at end of file then char-ready? returns #t.

Rationale: The char-ready? procedure exists to make it possible for a program to accept characters from interactive ports without getting stuck waiting for input. Any input editors as- sociated with such ports must ensure that characters whose existence has been asserted by char-ready? cannot be removed from the input. If char-ready? were to return #f at end of file, a port at end-of-file would be indistinguishable from an interactive port that has no ready characters.

Procedure: read-string k [port]

Reads the next k characters, or as many as are available before the end of file, from the textual input port into a newly allocated string in left-to-right order and returns the string. If no characters are available before the end of file, an end-of-file object is returned.

Procedure: read-u8 [port]

Returns the next byte available from the binary input port, updating the port to point to the following byte. If no more bytes are available, an end-of-file object is returned.

Procedure: peek-u8 [port]

Returns the next byte available from the binary input port, but without updating the port to point to the following byte. If no more bytes are available, an end-of-file object is returned.

Procedure: u8-ready? [port]

Returns #t if a byte is ready on the binary input port and returns #f otherwise. If u8-ready? returns #t then the next read-u8 operation on the given port is guaranteed not to hang. If the port is at end of file then u8-ready? returns #t.

Procedure: read-bytevector k [port]

Reads the next k bytes, or as many as are available before the end of file, from the binary input port into a newly allocated bytevector in left-to-right order and returns the bytevector. If no bytes are available before the end of file, an end-of-file object is returned.

Procedure: read-bytevector! bytevector [port [start [end]]]

Reads the next end − start bytes, or as many as are available before the end of file, from the binary input port into bytevector in left-to-right order beginning at the start position. If end is not supplied, reads until the end of bytevector has been reached. If start is not supplied, reads beginning at position 0. Returns the number of bytes read. If no bytes are available, an end-of-file object is returned.

Output

If port is omitted from any output procedure, it defaults to the value returned by (current-output-port). It is an error to attempt an output operation on a closed port.

The return type of these methods is void.

Procedure: write obj [port]

Writes a representation of obj to the given textual output port. Strings that appear in the written representation are enclosed in quotation marks, and within those strings backslash and quotation mark characters are escaped by backslashes. Symbols that contain non-ASCII characters are escaped with vertical lines. Character objects are written using the #\ notation.

If obj contains cycles which would cause an infinite loop using the normal written representation, then at least the objects that form part of the cycle must be represented using datum labels. Datum labels must not be used if there are no cycles.

Procedure: write-shared obj [port]

The write-shared procedure is the same as write, except that shared structure must be represented using datum labels for all pairs and vectors that appear more than once in the output.

Procedure: write-simple obj [port]

The write-simple procedure is the same as write, except that shared structure is never represented using datum labels. This can cause write-simple not to terminate if obj contains circular structure.

Procedure: display obj [port]

Writes a representation of obj to the given textual output port. Strings that appear in the written representation are output as if by write-string instead of by write. Symbols are not escaped. Character objects appear in the representation as if written by write-char instead of by write. The display representation of other objects is unspecified.

Procedure: newline [port]

Writes an end of line to textual output port. This is done using the println method of the Java class java.io.PrintWriter.

Procedure: write-char char [port]

Writes the character char (not an external representation of the character) to the given textual output port.

Procedure: write-string string [port [start [end]]]

Writes the characters of string from start to end in left-to-right order to the textual output port.

Procedure: write-u8 byte [port]

Writes the byte to the given binary output port.

Procedure: write-bytevector bytevector [port [start [end]]]

Writes the bytes of bytevector from start to end in left-to-right order to the binary output port.

Procedure: flush-output-port [port]

Procedure: force-output [port]

Forces any pending output on port to be delivered to the output file or device and returns an unspecified value. If the port argument is omitted it defaults to the value returned by (current-output-port). (The name force-output is older, while R6RS added flush-output-port. They have the same effect.)

Prompts for interactive consoles (REPLs)

When an interactive input port is used for a read-eval-print-loop (REPL or console) it is traditional for the REPL to print a short prompt string to signal that the user is expected to type an expression. These prompt strings can be customized.

Variable: input-prompt1

Variable: input-prompt2

These are fluid variable whose values are string templates with placeholders similar to printf-style format. The placeholders are expanded (depending on the current state), and the resulting string printed in front of the input line.

The input-prompt1 is used normally. For multi-line input commands (for example if the first line is incomplete), input-prompt1 is used for the first line of each command, while input-prompt2 is used for subsequent “continuation” lines.

The following placeholders are handled:

%%

A literal ‘%’.

%N

The current line number. This is (+ 1 (port-line port)).

%nPc

Insert padding at this possion, repeating the following character c as needed to bring the total number of columns of the prompt to that specified by the digits n.

%Pc

Same as %nPc, but n defaults to the number of columns in the initial prompt from the expansion of input-prompt1. This is only meaningful when expanding input-prompt2 for continuation lines.

%{hidden%}

Same as hidden, but the characters of hidden are assumed to have zero visible width. Can be used for ANSI escape sequences to change color or style:

(set! input-prompt1 "%{\e[48;5;51m%}{Kawa:%N} %{\e[0m%}")

The above changes both the text and the background color (to a pale blue).

%M

Insert a “message” string. Not normally used by Kawa, but supported by JLine.

These variables can be initialized by the command-line arguments console:prompt1=prompt1 and console:prompt2=prompt2, respectively. If these are not specified, languages-specific defaults are used. For example for Scheme the default value of input-prompt1 is "#|kawa:%N|# " and input-prompt2 is "#|$P.%N| ". These have the form of Scheme comments, to make it easier to cut-and-paste.

If input-prompt1 (respectively input-prompt2) does not contain an escape sequence (either "%{ or the escape character "\e") then ANSI escape sequences are added to to highlight the prompt. (Under DomTerm this sets the prompt style, which can be customised with CSS but defaults to a light green background; if using JLine the background is set to light green.)

For greater flexibility, you can also set a prompter procedure.

Procedure: set-input-port-prompter! port prompter

Set the prompt procedure associated with port to prompter, which must be a one-argument procedure taking an input port, and returning a string. The procedure is called before reading the first line of a command; its return value is used as the first-line prompt.

The prompt procedure can have side effects. In Bash shell terms: It combines the features of PROMPT_COMMAND and PS1.

The initial prompter is default-prompter, which returns the expansion of input-prompt1.

Procedure: input-port-prompter port

Get the prompt procedure associated with port.

Procedure: default-prompter port

The default prompt procedure. Normally (i.e. when input-port-read-state is a space) returns input-prompt1 after expanding the %-placeholders. Can also expand input-prompt2 when input-port-read-state is not whitespace.

Line numbers and other input port properties

Function: port-column input-port

Function: port-line input-port

Return the current column number or line number of input-port, using the current input port if none is specified. If the number is unknown, the result is #f. Otherwise, the result is a 0-origin integer - i.e. the first character of the first line is line 0, column 0. (However, when you display a file position, for example in an error message, we recommend you add 1 to get 1-origin integers. This is because lines and column numbers traditionally start with 1, and that is what non-programmers will find most natural.)

Procedure: set-port-line! port line

Set (0-origin) line number of the current line of port to num.

Procedure: input-port-line-number port

Get the line number of the current line of port, which must be a (non-binary) input port. The initial line is line 1. Deprecated; replaced by (+ 1 (port-line port)).

Procedure: set-input-port-line-number! port num

Set line number of the current line of port to num. Deprecated; replaced by (set-port-line! port (- num 1)).

Procedure: input-port-column-number port

Get the column number of the current line of port, which must be a (non-binary) input port. The initial column is column 1. Deprecated; replaced by (+ 1 (port-column port)).

Procedure: input-port-read-state port

Returns a character indicating the current read state of the port. Returns #\Return if not current doing a read, #\" if reading a string; #\| if reading a comment; #\( if inside a list; and #\Space when otherwise in a read. The result is intended for use by prompt prcedures, and is not necessarily correct except when reading a new-line.

Variable: symbol-read-case

A symbol that controls how read handles letters when reading a symbol. If the first letter is ‘U’, then letters in symbols are upper-cased. If the first letter is ‘D’ or ‘L’, then letters in symbols are down-cased. If the first letter is ‘I’, then the case of letters in symbols is inverted. Otherwise (the default), the letter is not changed. (Letters following a ‘\’ are always unchanged.) The value of symbol-read-case only checked when a reader is created, not each time a symbol is read.

Miscellaneous

Variable: port-char-encoding

Controls how bytes in external files are converted to/from internal Unicode characters. Can be either a symbol or a boolean. If port-char-encoding is #f, the file is assumed to be a binary file and no conversion is done. Otherwise, the file is a text file. The default is #t, which uses a locale-dependent conversion. If port-char-encoding is a symbol, it must be the name of a character encoding known to Java. For all text files (that is if port-char-encoding is not #f), on input a #\Return character or a #\Return followed by #\Newline are converted into plain #\Newline.

This variable is checked when the file is opened; not when actually reading or writing. Here is an example of how you can safely change the encoding temporarily:

(define (open-binary-input-file name)
  (fluid-let ((port-char-encoding #f)) (open-input-file name)))

Variable: *print-base*

The number base (radix) to use by default when printing rational numbers. Must be an integer between 2 and 36, and the default is of course 10. For example setting *print-base* to 16 produces hexadecimal output.

Variable: *print-radix*

If true, prints an indicator of the radix used when printing rational numbers. If *print-base* is respectively 2, 8, or 16, then #b, #o or #x is written before the number; otherwise #Nr is written, where N is the base. An exception is when *print-base* is 10, in which case a period is written after the number, to match Common Lisp; this may be inappropriate for Scheme, so is likely to change.

Variable: *print-right-margin*

The right margin (or line width) to use when pretty-printing.

Variable: *print-miser-width*

If this an integer, and the available width is less or equal to this value, then the pretty printer switch to the more miser compact style.

Variable: *print-xml-indent*

When writing to XML, controls pretty-printing and indentation. If the value is 'always or 'yes force each element to start on a new suitably-indented line. If the value is 'pretty only force new lines for elements that won’t fit completely on a line. The the value is 'no or unset, don’t add extra whitespace.

String and bytevector ports
Input
Output
Prompts for interactive consoles (REPLs)
Line numbers and other input port properties
Miscellaneous

Up: Input, output, and file handling

Previous: Reading and writing whole files

Next: Formatted Output (Common-Lisp-style)

Processes

A process is a native (operating-system-level) application or program that runs separately from the current virtual machine.

Many programming languages have facilities to allow access to system processes (commands). (For example Java has java.lang.Process and java.lang.ProcessBuilder.) These facilities let you send data to the standard input, extract the resulting output, look at the return code, and sometimes even pipe commands together. However, this is rarely as easy as it is using the old Bourne shell; for example command substitution is awkward. Kawa’s solution is based on these two ideas:

A “process expression” (typically a function call) evaluates to a LProcess value, which provides access to a Unix-style (or Windows) process.

In a context requiring a string (or a bytevector), an LProcess is automatically converted to a string (or bytevector) comprising the standard output from the process.

Creating a process

The most flexible way to start a process is with either the run-process procedure or the &`{command} syntax for process literals.

Procedure: run-process process-keyword-argument* command

Creates a process object, specifically a gnu.kawa.functions.LProcess object. A process-keyword-argument can be used to set various options, as discussed below.

The command is the process command-line (name and arguments). It can be an array of strings, in which case those are used as the command arguments directly:

(run-process ["ls" "-l"])

The command can also be a single string, which is split (tokenized) into command arguments separated by whitespace. Quotation groups words together just like traditional shells:

(run-process "cmd a\"b 'c\"d k'l m\"n'o")
   ⇒ (run-process ["cmd"   "ab 'cd"   "k'l m\"no"])

The syntax shorthand &`{command} or &sh{command} (discussed below) is usually more convenient.

process-keyword-argument ::=
    process-redirect-argument
  | process-environment-argument
  | process-misc-argument

We discuss process-redirect-argument and process-environment-argument later. The process-misc-argument options are just the following:

shell: shell

Currently, shell must be one of #f (which is ignored) or #t. The latter means to use an external shell to tokenize the command. I.e. the following are equivalent:

(run-process shell: #t "command")
(run-process ["/bin/sh" "-c" "command"])

directory: dir

Change the working directory of the new process to dir.

Process literals

A simple process literal is a kind of named literal that uses the backtick character (`) as the cname. For example:

&`{date --utc}

This is equivalent to:

(run-process "date --utc")

In general the following are roughly equivalent (using string quasi-literals):

&`[args...]{command}
(run-process args... &{command})

The reason for the “roughly” is if command contains escaped sub-expressions; in that case &` may process the resulting values differently from plain string-substitution, as discussed below.

If you use &sh instead of &` then a shell is used:

&sh{rm *.class}

which is equivalent to:

&`{/bin/sh -c "rm *.class"}

In general, the following are equivalent:

&sh[args...]{command}
&`[shell: #t args...]{command}

Process values and process output

The value returned from a call to run-process or a process literal is an instance of gnu.kawa.functions.LProcess. This class extends java.lang.Process, so you can treat it as any other Process object.

#|kawa:1|# (define p1 &`{date --utc})
#|kawa:2|# (p1:toString)
gnu.kawa.functions.LProcess@377dca04
#|kawa:3|# (write p1)
gnu.kawa.functions.LProcess@377dca04

What makes an LProcess interesting is that it is also a blob, which is automatically converted to a string (or bytevector) in a context that requires it. The contents of the blob comes from the standard output of the process. The blob is evaluated lazily, so data it is only collected when requested.

#|kawa:4|# (define s1 ::string p1)
#|kawa:5|# (write s1)
"Wed Jan  1 01:18:21 UTC 2014\n"
#|kawa:6|# (define b1 ::bytevector p1)
(write b1)
#u8(87 101 100 32 74 97 110 ... 52 10)

The display procedure prints it in “human” form, as a string:

#|kawa:7|# (display p1)
Wed Jan  1 01:18:21 UTC 2014

This is also the default REPL formatting:

#|kawa:8|# &`{date --utc}
Wed Jan  1 01:18:22 UTC 2014

When you type a command to a shell, its output goes to the console, Similarly, in a REPL the output from the process is copied to the console output - which can sometimes by optimized by letting the process inherit its standard output from the Kawa process.

Substitution and tokenization

To substitute the variable or the result of an expression in the command line use the usual syntax for quasi literals:

(define filename (make-temporary-file))
&sh{run-experiment >&[filename]}

Since a process is convertible a string, we need no special syntax for command substitution:

`{echo The directory is: &[&`{pwd}]}

or equivalently:

`{echo The directory is: &`{pwd}}

Things get more interesting when considering the interaction between substitution and tokenization. This is not simple string interpolation. For example, if an interpolated value contains a quote character, we want to treat it as a literal quote, rather than a token delimiter. This matches the behavior of traditional shells. There are multiple cases, depending on whether the interpolation result is a string or a vector/list, and depending on whether the interpolation is inside quotes.

If the value is a string, and we’re not inside quotes, then all non-whitespace characters (including quotes) are literal, but whitespace still separates tokens:

(define v1 "a b'c ")
&`{cmd x y&[v1]z}   ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "x" "ya" "b'c" "z"])

If the value is a string, and we are inside single quotes, all characters (including whitespace) are literal.

&`{cmd 'x y&[v1]z'}   ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "x ya b'c z"])

Double quotes work the same except that newline is an argument separator. This is useful when you have one filename per line, and the filenames may contain spaces, as in the output from find:

&`{ls -l "&`{find . -name '*.pdf'}"}

This solves a problem that is quite painful with traditional shells.

If the value is a vector or list (of strings), and we’re not inside quotes, then each element of the array becomes its own argument, as-is:

(define v2 ["a b" "c\"d"])
&`{cmd &[v2]}  ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "a b" "c\"d"])

However, if the enclosed expression is adjacent to non-space non-quote characters, those are prepended to the first element, or appended to the last element, respectively.

&`{cmd x&[v2]y}   ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "xa b" "c\"dy"])
&`{cmd x&[[]]y}   ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "xy"])

This behavior is similar to how shells handle "$@" (or "${name[@]}" for general arrays), though in Kawa you would leave off the quotes.

Note the equivalence:

&`{&[array]}   ⇒  (run-process array)

If the value is a vector or list (of strings), and we are inside quotes, it is equivalent to interpolating a single string resulting from concatenating the elements separated by a space:

&`{cmd "&[v2]"}
 ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "a b c\"d"])

This behavior is similar to how shells handle "$*" (or "${name[*]}" for general arrays).

If the value is the result of a call to unescaped-data then it is parsed as if it were literal. For example a quote in the unescaped data may match a quote in the literal:

(define vu (unescaped-data "b ' c d '"))
&`{cmd 'a &[vu]z'}   ⇒  (run-process ["cmd" "a b " "c" "d" "z"])

If we’re using a shell to tokenize the command, then we add quotes or backslashes as needed so that the shell will tokenize as described above:

(define authors ["O'Conner" "de Beauvoir"])
&sh{list-books &[authors]}

The command passed to the shell is:

list-books 'O'\''Conner' 'de Beauvoir

Having quoting be handled by the $construct$:sh implementation automatically eliminates common code injection problems.

Smart tokenization only happens when using the quasi-literal forms such as &`{command}. You can of course use string templates with run-process:

(run-process &{echo The directory is: &`{pwd}})

However, in that case there is no smart tokenization: The template is evaluated to a string, and then the resulting string is tokenized, with no knowledge of where expressions were substituted.

Input/output redirection

You can use various keyword arguments to specify standard input, output, and error streams. For example to lower-case the text in in.txt, writing the result to out.txt, you can do:

&`[in-from: "in.txt" out-to: "out.txt"]{tr A-Z a-z}

or:

(run-process in-from: "in.txt" out-to: "out.txt" "tr A-Z a-z")

A process-redirect-argument can be one of the following:

in: value

The value is evaluated, converted to a string (as if using display), and copied to the input file of the process. The following are equivalent:

&`[in: "text\n"]{command}
&`[in: &`{echo "text"}]{command}

You can pipe the output from command1 to the input of command2 as follows:

&`[in: &`{command1}]{command2}

in-from: path

The process reads its input from the specified path, which can be any value coercible to a filepath.

out-to: path

The process writes its output to the specified path.

err-to: path

Similarly for the error stream.

out-append-to: path
err-append-to: path

Similar to out-to and err-to, but append to the file specified by path, instead of replacing it.

in-from: ’pipe
out-to: ’pipe
err-to: ’pipe

Does not set up redirection. Instead, the specified stream is available using the methods getOutputStream, getInputStream, or getErrorStream, respectively, on the resulting Process object, just like Java’s ProcessBuilder.Redirect.PIPE.

in-from: ’inherit
out-to: ’inherit
err-to: ’inherit

Inherits the standard input, output, or error stream from the current JVM process.

out-to: port
err-to: port

Redirects the standard output or error of the process to the specified port.

out-to: ’current
err-to: ’current

Same as out-to: (current-output-port), or err-to: (current-error-port), respectively.

in-from: port
in-from: ’current

Re-directs standard input to read from the port (or (current-input-port)). It is unspecified how much is read from the port. (The implementation is to use a thread that reads from the port, and sends it to the process, so it might read to the end of the port, even if the process doesn’t read it all.)

err-to: ’out

Redirect the standard error of the process to be merged with the standard output.

The default for the error stream (if neither err-to or err-append-to is specified) is equivalent to err-to: 'current.

Note: Writing to a port is implemented by copying the output or error stream of the process. This is done in a thread, which means we don’t have any guarantees when the copying is finished. (In the future we might change process-exit-wait (discussed later) wait for not only the process to finish, but also for these helper threads to finish.)

A here document is a form a literal string, typically multi-line, and commonly used in shells for the standard input of a process. You can use string literals or string quasi-literals for this. For example, this passes the string "line1\nline2\nline3\n" to the standard input of command:

(run-process [in: &{
    &|line1
    &|line2
    &|line3
    }] "command")

Note the use of &| to mark the end of ignored indentation.

Pipe-lines

Piping the output of one process as the input of another is in princple easy - just use the in: process argument. However, writing a multi-stage pipe-line quickly gets ugly:

&`[in: &`[in: "My text\n"]{tr a-z A-Z}]{wc}

The convenience macro pipe-process makes this much nicer:

(pipe-process
  "My text\n"
  &`{tr a-z A-Z}
  &`{wc})

Syntax: pipe-process input process*

All of the process expressions must be run-process forms, or equivalent &`{command} forms. The result of evaluating input becomes the input to the first process; the output from the first process becomes the input to the second process, and so on. The result of whole pipe-process expression is that of the last process.

Copying the output of one process to the input of the next is optimized: it uses a copying loop in a separate thread. Thus you can safely pipe long-running processes that produce huge output. This isn’t quite as efficient as using an operating system pipe, but is portable and works pretty well.

Setting the process environment

By default the new process inherits the system environment of the current (JVM) process as returned by System.getenv(), but you can override it. A process-environment-argument can be one of the following:

env-name: value

In the process environment, set the "name" to the specified value. For example:

&`[env-CLASSPATH: ".:classes"]{java MyClass}

NAME: value

Same as using the env-NAME option above, but only if the NAME is uppercase (i.e. if uppercasing NAME yields the same string). For example the previous example could be written:

&`[CLASSPATH: ".:classes"]{java MyClass}

environment: env

The env is evaluated and must yield a HashMap. This map is used as the system environment of the process.

Waiting for process exit

When a process finishes, it returns an integer exit code. The code is traditionally 0 on successful completion, while a non-zero code indicates some kind of failure or error.

Procedure: process-exit-wait process

The process expression must evaluate to a process (any java.lang.Process object). This procedure waits for the process to finish, and then returns the exit code as an int.

(process-exit-wait (run-process "echo foo")) ⇒ 0

Procedure: process-exit-ok? process

Calls process-exit-wait, and then returns #false if the process exited it 0, and returns #true otherwise.

This is useful for emulating the way traditional shell do logic control flow operations based on the exit code. For example in sh you might write:

if grep Version Makefile >/dev/null
then echo found Version
else echo no Version
fi

The equivalent in Kawa:

(if (process-exit-ok? &`{grep Version Makefile})
  &`{echo found}
  &`{echo not found})

Strictly speaking these are not quite the same, since the Kawa version silently throws away the output from grep (because no-one has asked for it). To match the output from the sh, you can use out-to: 'inherit:

(if (process-exit-ok? &`[out-to: 'inherit]{grep Version Makefile})
  &`{echo found}
  &`{echo not found})

Exiting the current process

Procedure: exit [code]

Exits the Kawa interpreter, and ends the Java session. Returns the value of code to the operating system: The code must be integer, or the special values #f (equivalent to -1), or #t (equivalent to 0). If code is not specified, zero is returned. The code is a status code; by convention a non-zero value indicates a non-standard (error) return.

Before exiting, finally-handlers (as in try-finally, or the after procedure of dynamic-wind) are executed, but only in the current thread, and only if the current thread was started normally. (Specifically if we’re inside an ExitCalled block with non-zero nesting - see gnu.kawa.util.ExitCalled.) Also, JVM shutdown hooks are executed - which includes flushing buffers of output ports. (Specifically Writer objects registered with the WriterManager.)

Procedure: emergency-exit [code]

Exits the Kawa interpreter, and ends the Java session. Communicates an exit value in the same manner as exit. Unlike exit, neither finally-handlers nor shutdown hooks are executed.

Deprecated functions

Procedure: make-process command envp

Creates a <java.lang.Process> object, using the specified command and envp. The command is converted to an array of Java strings (that is an object that has type <java.lang.String[]>. It can be a Scheme vector or list (whose elements should be Java strings or Scheme strings); a Java array of Java strings; or a Scheme string. In the latter case, the command is converted using command-parse. The envp is process environment; it should be either a Java array of Java strings, or the special #!null value.

Except for the representation of envp, this is similar to:

(run-process environment: envp command)

Procedure: system command

Runs the specified command, and waits for it to finish. Returns the return code from the command. The return code is an integer, where 0 conventionally means successful completion. The command can be any of the types handled by make-process.

Equivalent to:

(process-exit-wait (make-process command #!null))

Variable: command-parse

The value of this variable should be a one-argument procedure. It is used to convert a command from a Scheme string to a Java array of the constituent "words". The default binding, on Unix-like systems, returns a new command to invoke "/bin/sh" "-c" concatenated with the command string; on non-Unix-systems, it is bound to tokenize-string-to-string-array.

Procedure: tokenize-string-to-string-array command

Uses a java.util.StringTokenizer to parse the command string into an array of words. This splits the command using spaces to delimit words; there is no special processing for quotes or other special characters. (This is the same as what java.lang.Runtime.exec(String) does.)

Creating a process
Process literals
Process values and process output
Substitution and tokenization
Input/output redirection
Pipe-lines
Setting the process environment
Waiting for process exit
Exiting the current process
Deprecated functions

Up: Miscellaneous topics

Previous: System inquiry

Next: Time-related functions

Record types

The define-record-type form can be used for creating new data types, called record types. A predicate, constructor, and field accessors and modifiers are defined for each record type. The define-record-type feature is specified by SRFI-9, which is implemented by many modern Scheme implementations.

Syntax: define-record-type type-name (constructor-name field-tag ...) predicate-name (field-tag accessor-name [modifier-name]) ...

The form define-record-type is generative: each use creates a new record type that is distinct from all existing types, including other record types and Scheme’s predefined types. Record-type definitions may only occur at top-level (there are two possible semantics for ‘internal’ record-type definitions, generative and nongenerative, and no consensus as to which is better).

An instance of define-record-type is equivalent to the following definitions:

The type-name is bound to a representation of the record type itself.

The constructor-name is bound to a procedure that takes as many arguments as there are field-tags in the (constructor-name ...) subform and returns a new type-name record. Fields whose tags are listed with constructor-name have the corresponding argument as their initial value. The initial values of all other fields are unspecified.

The predicate-name is a predicate that returns #t when given a value returned by constructor-name and #f for everything else.

Each accessor-name is a procedure that takes a record of type type-name and returns the current value of the corresponding field. It is an error to pass an accessor a value which is not a record of the appropriate type.

Each modifier-name is a procedure that takes a record of type type-name and a value which becomes the new value of the corresponding field. The result (in Kawa) is the empty value #!void. It is an error to pass a modifier a first argument which is not a record of the appropriate type.

Set!ing the value of any of these identifiers has no effect on the behavior of any of their original values.

Here is an example of how you can define a record type named pare with two fields x and y:

(define-record-type pare
  (kons x y)
  pare?
  (x kar set-kar!)
  (y kdr))

The above defines kons to be a constructor, kar and kdr to be accessors, set-kar! to be a modifier, and pare? to be a predicate for pares.

(pare? (kons 1 2))        ⇒ #t
(pare? (cons 1 2))        ⇒ #f
(kar (kons 1 2))          ⇒ 1
(kdr (kons 1 2))          ⇒ 2
(let ((k (kons 1 2)))
  (set-kar! k 3)
  (kar k))                ⇒ 3

Kawa compiles the record type into a nested class. If the define-record-type appears at module level, the result is a class that is a member of the module class. For example if the above pare class is define in a module parelib, then the result is a class named pare with the internal JVM name parelib$pare. The define-record-type can appear inside a procedure, in which case the result is an inner class.

The nested class has a name derived from the type-name. If the type-name is valid Java class name, that becomes the name of the Java class. If the type-name has the form <name> (for example <pare>), then name is used, if possible, for the Java class name. Otherwise, the name of the Java class is derived by "mangling" the type-name. In any case, the package is the same as that of the surrounding module.

Kawa generates efficient code for the resulting functions, without needing to use run-time reflection.

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Importing from a library

Next: Creating New Record Types On-the-fly

Running Command Scripts

If you write a Kawa application, it is convenient to be able to execute it directly (from the command line or clicking an icon, say), without have to explicitly run kawa or java. On Unix-like systems the easiest way to do this is to write a small shell script that runs your Kawa application.

For modest-sized applications it is convenient if the shell script and the Kawa code can be in the same file. Unix-like systems support a mechanism where a script can specify a program that should execute it. The convention is that the first line of the file should start with the two characters ‘#!’ followed by the absolute path of the program that should process (interpret) the script.

(Windows has batch files, which are similar.)

This convention works well for script languages that use ‘#’ to indicate the start of a comment, since the interpreter will automatically ignore the line specifying the interpreter filename. Scheme, however, uses ‘#’ as a multi-purpose prefix, and Kawa specifically uses ‘#!’ as a prefix for various Special named constants such as #!optional.

Kawa does recognize the three-character sequence ‘#!/’ at the beginning of a file as special, and ignores it. Here is an example:

#!/usr/local/bin/kawa
(format #t "The command-line was:~{ ~w~}~%" (command-line))

If you copy this text to a file named /home/me/bin/scm-echo, set the execute permission, and make sure it is in your PATH, then you can execute it just by naming it on command line:

$ chmod +x /home/me/bin/scm-echo
$ PATH=/home/me/bin:$PATH
$ scm-env a b
The command-line was: "/home/me/bin/scm-echo" "a" "b"

The system kernel will automatically execute kawa, passing it the filename as an argument.

Note that the full path-name of the kawa interpreter must be hard-wired into the script. This means you may have to edit the script depending on where Kawa is installed on your system. Another possible problem is that the interpreter must be an actual program, not a shell script. Depending on how you configure and install Kawa, kawa can be a real program or a script. You can avoid both problems by the env program, available on most modern Unix-like systems:

#!/usr/bin/env kawa
(format #t "The command-line was:~{ ~w~}~%" (command-line))

This works the same way, but assumes kawa is in the command PATH.

Setting kawa options in the script

If you need to specify extra arguments to kawa, you can run arbitrary shell command inside Scheme block comments. Here is an example:

#!/bin/sh
#|
exec kawa out:base=16 out:radix=yes "$0" "$*"
|#
(format #t "The command-line is:~{ ~w~}.~%" (command-line))
(display "It has ")
(display (apply + (map string-length (command-line))))
(display " characters.")
(newline)

The trick is to hide the shell code from Kawa inside a #|...|# block-comment. The start of the block comment is a line starting with a #, so it is treated as a comment by the shell. You can then invoke kawa (or java directly) as you prefer, setting up class-path and jars as needed, and passing whatever arguments you want. (The shell replaces the "$0" by the name of the script, and replaces the "$@" by the remaining arguments passed to the script.) You need to make sure the shell finishes before it reaches the end of the block comment or the Scheme code, which would confuse it. The example uses exec, which tells the shell to replace itself by kawa; an alternative is to use the shell exit command.

If you copy the above file to /tmp/sch-echo and make that file executable, you can run it directly:

$ /tmp/scm-echo "a b" "c d"
The command-line is: "/tmp/scm-echo" "a b c d".
It has #x14 characters.

When the Kawa reader sees the initial #/ it sets the command name to the file name, so it can be used by a future call to (command-name). If you want to override this you can use the -Dkawa.command.name=name option.

Using comments this way has the advantage that you have the option of running the script “manually” if you prefer:

$ kawa /tmp/scm-echo out:base=8 "x y"
The command-line is: "/tmp/scm-echo" "out:base=8" "x y".
It has 26 characters.

Other ways to pass options using meta-arg or –script

An argument consisting of just a \ (backslash) causes Kawa to read the second line looking for options. (Quotes and backslashes work like in the shell.) These replace the backslash in the command line.

This is a less verbose mechanism, but it requires an absolute path to kawa, due to shell limitations.

#!/usr/bin/kawa \
  --scheme --full-tailcalls
(format #t "The command-line is:~{ ~w~}.~%" (command-line))

In this case the effective command line received by Kawa will be --scheme, --full-tailcalls, followed by the script filename, followed by other arguments specified when running the script.

The backslash used this way originated in scsh where it is called the meta-arg. (Unlike scsh, Kawa’s #! is not a block comment, but a rest-of-line, though the backslash causes the following line to also be skipped.)

An alternative method is to use the --script2 option, which tells Kawa to execute the script after ignoring the initial two lines. For example:

#!/bin/sh
exec kawa --commonlisp out:base=16 --script2 "$0" "$@"
(setq xx 20) (display xx) (newline)

This is slightly more compact than using block-comments as shown earlier, but it has the disadvantage that you can’t explicitly use kawa or java to run the script unless you make sure to pass it the --script2 option.

Scripts for compiled code

If you compile your Kawa application to class files (or better: a jar file), you probably still want to write a small shell script to set things up. Here is one method:

#!/bin/sh
export CLASSPATH=/my/path
exec kawa -Dkawa.command.name="$0" foo "$@"

Using the kawa front-end is a convenience, since it automatically sets up the paths for the Kawa classes, and (if enabled) it provides readline support for the default input port.

Setting the kawa.command.name property to "$0" (the filename used to invoke the script) enables (command-line) to use the script name as the command name.

You can invoke java directly, which is necessary when running a jar file:

#!/bin/sh
exec java -cp /path/to/kawa -Dkawa.command.name="$0" foo.jar "$@"

Setting kawa options in the script
Other ways to pass options using meta-arg or –script
Scripts for compiled code

Up: How to start up and run Kawa

Previous: Command-line arguments

Next: The REPL (read-eval-print-loop) console

Self-configuring web page scripts

Kawa makes it easy to set up a web site without configuration files. Instead, the mapping from request URL to web page script matches the layout of files in the application directory.

Many web servers make it easy to execute a script using a script processor which is selected depending on the extension of the requested URL. That is why you see lots of URLs that end in .cgi, .php, or .jsp. This is bad, because it exposes the server-side implementation to the user: Not only are such URLs ugly, but they make it difficult to change the server without breaking people’s bookmarks and search engines. A server will usually provide a mechanism to use prettier URLs, but doing so requires extra effort, so many web-masters don’t.

If you want a script to be executed in response to a URL http://host/app/foo/bar you give the script the name app/foo/bar, in the appropriate server “application” directory (as explained below). You get to pick the name bar. Or you can use the name bar.html, even though the file named bar.html isn’t actually an html file - rather it produces html when evaluated. Or better: just use a name without an extension at all. Kawa figures out what kind of script it is based on the content of the file, rather than the file name. Once Kawa has found a script, it looks at the first line to see if it can recognize the kind (language) of the script. Normally this would be a comment that contains the name of a programming language that Kawa knows about. For example:

;; Hello world page script written in -*- scheme -*- 
#<p>Hello, <b>&(request-remote-host)</b>!</p>

(Using the funny-looking string -*- scheme -*- has the bonus is that it recognized by the Emacs text editor.)

A script named +default+ is run if there isn’t a matching script. For example assume the following is a file named +default.

;; This is -*- scheme -*-
(make-element 'p "servlet-path: " (request-servlet-path))

This becomes the default script for HTTP requests that aren’t handled by a more specific script. The request-servlet-path function returns the "servlet path", which is the part of the requested URL that is relative to the current web application. Thus a request for http://host:port/app/this/is/a/test will return:

servlet-path: /this/is/a/test

Using the OpenJDK built-in web server

The easiest way to run a Kawa web server is to use the web server built in to JDK 6 or later.

kawa --http-auto-handler context-path appdir --http-start port

This starts a web server that listens on the given port, using the files in directory appdir to handle requests that start with the given context-path. The context-path must start with a "/" (one is added if needed), and it is recommended that it also end with a "/" (otherwise you might get some surprising behavior).

You can specify multiple --http-auto-handler options.

For example use the files in the current directory to handle all requests on the standard port 80 do:

kawa --http-auto-handler / . --http-start 80

There are some examples in the testsuite/webtest directory the Kawa source distribution. You can start the server thus:

bin/kawa --http-auto-handler / testsuite/webtest/ --http-start 8888

and then for example browse to http://localhost:8888/adder.scm.

For lots of information about the HTTP request, browse to http://localhost:8888/info/anything.

Using a servlet container

You can also can use a “servlet container” such as Tomcat or Glassfish with self-configuring script. See Servlets for information on how to install these servers, and the concept of web applications. Once you have these server installed, you create a web application with the following in the appdir/WEB-INF/web.xml configuration file:

<web-app>
  <display-name>Kawa auto-servlet</display-name>
  <servlet>
    <servlet-name>KawaPageServlet</servlet-name>
    <servlet-class>gnu.kawa.servlet.KawaPageServlet</servlet-class>
  </servlet>
  <servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>KawaPageServlet</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>
</web-app>

This creates a web application where all URLs are handled by the gnu.kawa.servlet.KawaPageServlet servlet class, which is included in the Kawa jar file. The KawaPageServlet class handles the searching and compiling described in this page.

Finding a matching script

When Kawa receives a request for:

http://host:port/appname/a/b/anything

it will look for a file:

appdir/a/b/anything

If such a file exists, the script will be executed, as described below. If not, it will look for a file name +default+ in the same directory. If that desn’t exist either, it will look for +default+ in the parent directory, then the grand-parent directory, and so on until it gets to the appname web application root directory. So the default script is this: appdir/+default.

If that doesn’t exist then Kawa returns a 404 "page not found" error.

Determining script language

Once Kawa has found a script file corresponding to a request URL, it needs to determine if this is a data file or a web page script, and in the latter case, what language it is written in.

Kawa recognizes the following "magic strings" in the first line of a script:

kawa:scheme

The Scheme language.

kawa:xquery

The XQuery language.

kawa:language

Some other language known to Kawa.

Kawa also recognizes Emacs-style "mode specifiers":

-*- scheme -*-

The Scheme language.

-*- xquery -*-

The XQuery language (though Emacs doesn’t know about XQuery).

-*- emacs-lisp -*-
-*- elisp -*-

The Emacs Lisp extension language.

-*- common-lisp -*-
-*- lisp -*-

The Common Lisp language.

Also, it also recognizes comments in the first two columns of the line:

;;

A Scheme or Lisp comment - assumed to be in the Scheme language.

(:

Start of an XQuery comment, so assumed to be in the XQuery language.

If Kawa doesn’t recognize the language of a script (and it isn’t named +default+) then it assumes the file is a data file. It asks the servlet engine to figure out the content type (using the getMimeType method of ServletContext), and just copies the file into the response.

Compilation and caching

Kawa automatically compiles a script into a class. The class is internal to the server, and is not written out to disk. (There is an unsupported option to write the compiled file to a class file, but there is no support to use previously-compiled classes.) The server then creates a module instance to handle the actual request, and runs the body (the run method) of the script class. On subsequence requests for the same script, the same class and instance are reused; only the run is re-executed.

If the script is changed, then it is re-compiled and a new module instance created. This makes it very easy to develop and modify a script. (Kawa for performance reasons doesn’t check more than once a second whether a script has been modified.)

Using the OpenJDK built-in web server
Using a servlet container
Finding a matching script
Determining script language
Compilation and caching

Up: Working with XML and HTML

Previous: Web page scripts

Next: Installing web page scripts as Servlets

Installing and using the source distribution

The Kawa release normally comes as a gzip-compressed tar file named ‘kawa-2.92_invoke.tar.gz’. Two methods are supporting for compiling the Kawa sources; choose whichever is most convenient for you.

One method uses the traditional GNU configure script, followed by running make. This works well on Unix-like systems, such as GNU/Linux. You can also use this method on Microsoft Windows, with the help of tools from MinGW or Cygwin.

The other method uses the ant command, a Java-based build system released by Apache’s Jakarta project. This uses an build.xml file in place of Makefiles, and works on non-Unix systems such as Microsoft Windows. However, the ant method does not support all the features of the configure+make method.

Build Kawa using configure and make

(See below for some notes for building on Microsoft Windows.)

If you have a tar.gz file, first unpack that in your build directory:

tar xzf kawa-2.92_invoke.tar.gz
cd kawa-2.92_invoke

If you’re building from the Git repository, you need to generate configure and some other files. This is easiest done with the autogen.sh script:

./autogen.sh

Then you must configure the sources. This you do in the same way you configure most other GNU software. Normally you can just run the configure script with no arguments:

./configure

The configure script takes a number of options.

If you have installed Kawa before, make sure your CLASSPATH does not include old versions of Kawa, or other classes that may conflict with the new ones.

Then you need to compile all the .java source files. Just run make:

make

This assumes that ‘java’ and ‘javac’ are the java interpreter and compiler, respectively.

It has been reported that parallel make doesn’t work, so don’t use the -j2 or above options.

You can now test the system by running Kawa in place:

java kawa.repl

or you can run the test suite:

make check

or you can install the compiled files:

make install

This will install your classes into $PREFIX/share/java (and its sub-directories). Here $PREFIX is the directory you specified to configure with the --prefix option, or /usr/local if you did not specify a --prefix option.

To use the installed files, you need to set CLASSPATH so that $PREFIX/share/java/kawa.jar is in the path:

CLASSPATH=$PREFIX/share/java/kawa.jar
export CLASSPATH

This is done automatically if you use the ‘kawa’ script.

Configure options

The configure script takes a number of options. The --help switch gives you a list of options. The following are some of the more common or important ones.

--prefix=install-dir
--prefix install-dir

By default make install will install the compiled .jar files info /usr/local/share/java, the kawa command into /usr/local/bin, and so on in /usr/local. The --prefix option causes the files to be installed under install-dir instead of /usr/local. For example to install the .jar in /opt/kawa/share/java and otherwise use /opt/kawa do:

./configure --prefix=/opt/kawa

--with-java-source=version

As distributed, the Kawa source code requires Java 7. If you only have Java 6 or Java 5, use the --with-java-source option:

./configure --with-java-source=5

Kawa no longer supports older verisons of Java (JDK 1.4 or older). It might be possible to use a tool like Retroweaver on the Kawa .jar to fix up Java 5 dependencies. Contact the Kawa author if you want to be a tester for this.

--with-docbook-stylesheet[=path]

Build the documentation (this manual) as an electronic book (in ebook format) or a website, using the DocBook xslt stylesheets. (You can build the documentation without DocBook, but using it enables nicer-looking and more functional documentation.)

The stylesheets are found using path; the file path/epub3/chunk.xsl needs to exist. (For example, on Fedora 25 path can be /usr/share/sgml/docbook/xsl-ns-stylesheets.)

--with-domterm
--with-domterm=domterm_home

Compile with extra support for the DomTerm terminal emulator library, where domterm_home is such that domterm_home/lib/domterm.jar exists. (Some DomTerm support is built-in regardless.)

If you use this option along with --with-javafx then creating a new REPL window will create a DomTerm window.

As an optional convenience, you can use the domterm.jar in the Kawa binary distribution.

--with-jline3
--with-jline3=jline3.jar

Build support for using JLine 3, which is a library for handling console input, similar to GNU readline. If specified, the jline3.jar is added to the classpath of the generated kawa.sh or kawa shell program.

An advantage of --with-jline3 (compared to --enable-kawa-frontend) is that the former works without native code (on most Unix-like platforms), and it does not require a C wrapper program.

As an optional convenience, you can use the jline.jar in the Kawa binary distribution.

--with-domterm
--with-domterm=domterm.jar

Compile with extra support for the DomTerm terminal emulator library. (Some DomTerm support is built-in regardless.)

If you use this option along with --with-javafx then creating a new REPL window will create a DomTerm window.

As an optional convenience, you can use the domterm.jar in the Kawa binary distribution.

--with-jline3
--with-jline3=jline3.jar

Build support for using JLine 3, which is a library for handling console input, similar to GNU readline. If specified, the jline3.jar is added to the classpath of the generated kawa.sh or kawa shell program.

An advantage of --with-jline3 (compared to --enable-kawa-frontend) is that the former works without native code (on most Unix-like platforms), and it does not require a C wrapper program.

As an optional convenience, you can use the jline.jar in the Kawa binary distribution.

--with-servlet
--with-servlet=servlet-jar

Build support for servlets, which are used in web servers. This requires the servlet-api.jar (available various places including Tomcat or Glassfish), for javax.servlet.Servlet and related classes. If this class isn’t in your classpath, specify its location as servlet-jar. For example:

./configure --with-servlet=/path/to/servlet-api.jar 

--enable-jemacs

Build JEmacs (enable Emacs-like text editor) and support (a subset of) the Emacs Lisp language. JEmacs is a proof of concept - not really usable or maintained.

--with-javafx
--with-javafx=javafx-jar
--with-javafx=java-home

Set this flag to enable the convenience features for JavaFX. The JavaFX classes are included in JDK 8 (but not OpenJDK 8), and you don’t need to specify javafx-jar or java-home. For JDK 7 you need to specify javafx-jar (the path to javafx.rt) or java-home (the value of the $JAVA_HOME).

--with-android=android-jar

Build for the Android platform. This requires special instructons.

--enable-kawa-frontend

If you have the GNU ‘readline’ library installed, you might try adding the ‘--enable-kawa-frontend’ flag. This will build the ‘kawa’ front-end program, which provides input-line editing and an input history. You can get ‘readline’ from archives of GNU programs, including ftp://www.gnu.org/.

Note that using JLine, enabled by --with-jline3, is now recommended instead of using the readline frontend.

You may need to specify to make where to find the readline include files (with READLINE_INCLUDE_PATH) and the library (with READINE_LIB_PATH). For example on OS/X you need to do:

make READLINE_INCLUDE_PATH=-I/usr/local/unix/readline/include \
     READLINE_LIB_PATH=-L/usr/local/unix/readline/lib

Building on Windows using MinGW

The Kawa configure and make process assumes Unix-like tools, which you can get from the MinGW project. Download the MingGW Installation Manager, and use it to install at least mingw-developer-toolkit. (Also installing msys-groff avoids a minor problem building the documentation.)

The C:\MinGW\msys\1.0\msys.bat script creates a command window with the bash shell and the PATH set up as needed. Alternatively, you can use the standard Windows command prompt if you set your PATH as described in here.

Building on Windows using Cygwin

The free Cygwin environment can be used for building Kawa: The Kawa configure script recognizes Cygwin, and modifies the classpath to use Windows-style path separators.

Beyond the base packages, you probably want to install autoconf, automake, git, texinfo, groff, make, and diffutils.

Cygwin (unlike MinGW) has a current version of makeinfo, but an undiagnosed bug still prevents building kawa.info. You can work around that problem with touch doc/kawa.info.

Building the documentation

To build the documentation in a form suitable for a web-site do:

cd doc && make web/index.html

You can then point your browser at file:/kawa_srcdir/doc/web/index.html.

The above requires makeinfo from the texinfo package, and the DocBook XSLT tools.

If you don’t have the DocBook XSLT tools (but have makeinfo), you can build a more plain HTML version of the documentation:

cd doc && make kawa-html/index.html

In this case, point your browser at file:/kawa_srcdir/doc/kawa-html/index.html.

To build an EPUB file suitable for ebook readers, as well as enabling support for the kawa --browse-manual option, do:

cd doc && make kawa-manual.epub

To build a pdf file suitable for printing or online viewing do:

cd doc && make kawa.pdf

The resulting kawa.pdf is somewhat unsatisfactory - when viewed online, links aren’t clickable. Furthermore, box drawing characters are missing.

Build Kawa using ant

Kawa now includes an Ant buildfile (build.xml). Ant is a part of the Apache Jakarta project. If you don’t hava Ant installed, get it from http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi. The build is entirely Java based and works equally well on *nix, Windows, and presumably most any other operating system.

Once Ant has been installed and configured (you may need to set the JAVA_HOME, and ANT_HOME environment variables), you should be able to change to the directory containing the build.xml file, and invoke the ‘ant’ command. With the default settings, a successful build will result in a kawa-2.92_invoke.jar in the current directory.

There are a few Ant "targets" of interest (they can be supplied on the Ant command line):

all

This is the default, it does classes and jar.

classes

Compiles all the files into *.class files into the directory specified by the build.dir property.

jar

Builds a jar into into the directory specified by the dist.dir property.

runw

Run Kawa in a GUI window.

clean

Deletes all files generated by the build, including the jar.

There is not yet a test target for running the testsuite.

There are various “properties" that control what ant does. You can override these on the command line or by editing the build.properties file in the same directory as build.xml. For example, the build.dir property tells ant where to build temporary files, and where to leave the resulting .jar file. For example, to leave the generated files in the sub-directory named BUILD do:

ant -Dbuild.dir=BUILD

A sample build.properties is provided and it contains comments explaining many of the options.

Here are a few general properties that help to customize your build:

build.dir

Path to put the temporary files used for building.

dist.dir

Path to put the resulting jar file.

version.local

A suffix to add to the version label for your customized version.

debug

Whether (true/false) the Javac "-g" option is enabled.

optimize

Whether (true/false) the Javac "-O" option is enabled.

Here are some Kawa-specific ones (all true/false): with-collections, with-references, with-awt, with-swing, enable-jemacs, and enable-servlet> See the sample build.properties for more information on these.

If you change any of the build properties, you will generally want to do an ‘ant clean’ before building again as the build is often not able to notice that kind of change. In the case of changing a directory path, you would want to do the clean before changing the path.

A special note for NetBeans users: For some reason the build-tools target which compiles an Ant task won’t compile with the classpath provided by NetBeans. You may do ‘ant build-tools’ from the command line outside of NetBeans, in which case you will not want to use the clean target as that will delete the tool files as well. You can use the clean-build and/or clean-dist targets as appropriate. Alternatively you can add ant.jar to the build-tools classpath by copying or linking it into a lib/ext directory in Kawa’s source directory (the one containing the build.xml file).

Build Kawa using configure and make
Building the documentation
Build Kawa using ant

Up: Getting and installing Kawa

Previous: Installing and using the binary distribution

Technical Support for Kawa

If you have a project that depends on Kawa or one of its component packages, you might do well to get paid priority support from Kawa’s author.

The base price is $2400 for one year. This entitles you to basic support by email or phone. Per <per@bothner.com> will answer techical questions about Kawa or its implementation, investigate bug reports, and suggest work-arounds. I may (at my discretion) provide fixes and enhancements (patches) for simple problems. Response for support requests received during the day (California time) will normally be within a few hours.

All support requests must come through a single designated contact person. If Kawa is important to your business, you probably want at least two contact people, doubling the price.

If the support contract is cancelled (by either party), remaining time will be prorated and refunded.

Per is also available for development projects.

Up: The Kawa Community

Previous: Acknowledgements and thanks

Next: Projects using Kawa

System inquiry

Variable: home-directory

A string containing the home directory of the user.

Procedure: command-line

Returns a nonempty list of immutable strings. The first element is an implementation-specific name for the running top-level program. The remaining elements are the command-line arguments, as passed to the main method (except for those flags processed by Kawa itself).

The first element will depend on how the Kawa module was invoked. Kawa uses the following rules to determine the command name:

If the property kawa.command.name is set, that is used. This variable can be set on the kawa command line, for example from a script:

kawa -Dkawa.command.name="$0" foo "$@"

This variable is also set implicitly by the meta-arg option. FIXME.

If we’re reading a source file that starts with the Unix command-file prefix ‘#!/’ then we use the name of the source file. The assumption is that such a file is an executable script.

If the Java property kawa.command.line is set, then we use that (after stripping off text that duplicates the remaining arguments). The kawa program sets this property to the command line used to invoke it (specifically the contents of the entire argv array), before invoking the java program.

If the Java property sun.java.command is set, then we use that (after stripping off text that duplicates the remaining arguments), and then prepending the string "java ". The OpenJDK java program sets this property.

If all else fails, the command name is "kawa".

Variable: command-line-arguments

Any command-line arguments (following flags processed by Kawa itself) are assigned to the global variable ‘command-line-arguments’, which is a vector of strings.

Procedure: process-command-line-assignments

Process any initial command-line options that set variables. These have the form name=value. Any such command-line options (at the start of the command-line) are processed and removed from the command-line.

$ java kawa.repl -- abc=123 def
#|kawa:1|# (write (command-line))
("java kawa.repl --" "abc=123" "def")
#|kawa:2|# (process-command-line-assignments)
#|kawa:3|# (write (command-line))
("java kawa.repl -- abc=123" "def")
#|kawa:4|# abc
123

This function is mostly useful for Kawa applications compiled with the --main option. (It is used to set XQuery external variables.)

Procedure: get-environment-variable name

Many operating systems provide each running process with an environment conisting of environment variables. (This environment is not to be confused with the Scheme environments that can be passed to eval.) Both the name and value of an environment variable are strings. The procedure get-environment-variable returns the value of the environment variable name, or #f if the environment variable is not found. (This uses the java.lang.System:getenv method.) It is an error to mutate the resulting string.

(get-environment-variable "PATH")
    ⇒ "/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin"

Procedure: get-environment-variables

Returns the names and values of all the environment variables as an alist, where the car of each entry is the name of an environment variable, and the cdr is its value, both as strings. It is an error to mutate any of the strings or the alist itself.

(get-environment-variables)
  ⇒ (("USER" . "root") ("HOME" . "/"))

Up: Miscellaneous topics

Previous: Android view construction

Next: Processes

Time-related functions

Procedure: current-second

Returns an inexact number represent the current time on the International Atomic Time (TAI) scale. The value 0.0 represents midnight on January 1, 1070 TAI (equivalent to 10 seconds before midnight Universal Time), and the value 1.0 represents on TAI second later. Neither high acuracy nor high precision are required; in particular returning Coordinated Universal Time plus a suitable constant might be the best an implementation cat do. The Kawa implementation just multiplies by 0.001 the result of calling the method currentTimeMillis in class java.lang.System.

Procedure: current-jiffy

Returns the number of jiffies as an exact integer that have elapses since an arbitrary implementation-defined epoch (instant). A jiffy is an implementation-defined fraction of a second which is defined by the return value of the jiffies-per-second procedure. The starting epoch (instant 0) is guaranteed to be constant during a run of the program, but may vary between runs. (At the time of writing, Kawa’s jiffy is one nano-second.)

Rationale: Jiffies are allowed to be implementation-dependent so that current-jiffy can execute with minimal overhead. It should be very likely that a compactly represented integer will suffice as the return value. Any particular jiffy size will be inappropriate some some implementations: a microsecond is too long for a very fast machine, while a much smaller unit would force many implementations to return integers which have to allocated for most calls, rendering current-jiffy less useful for accurate timing measurements.

Procedure: jiffies-per-second

Returns an exact integer representing the number of jiffies per SI second. This value is an implementation-specified constant. (At the time of writing, the value in Kawa is 1,000,000,000.)

Procedure: sleep time

Suspends the current thread for the specified time. The time can be either a pure number (in secords), or a quantity whose unit is a time unit (such as 10s).

Up: Miscellaneous topics

Previous: Processes

Next: Deprecated low-level functions

Lists and sequences

A sequence is a generalized array or list: Zero or more values treated as a compound value. Sequences have certain common operations, including indexing and iteration. (Technical note: Sequences generally implement the java.util.List interface, but Kawa will also treat strings and native Java arrays as sequences.)

Lists

In traditional Lisp-family languages, the list is the most important kind of sequence. (Don’t confuse Java’s List interface with Kawa’s use of the word list. They’re related, in that a Kawa “list” implements the List interface, so any list is also List, but not vice versa.)

A list is implemented as a chain of linked pairs. You can create a constant list by quoting a parenthesized list:

'(3 4 (10 20 30) "a string")

See Lists for details and operations.

Vectors

A vector is a sequence that is implemented by storing the elements side-by-side in memory. A vector uses less space than a list of the same length, and is generally more efficient than a list.

To create a vector you can use a bracketed list:

(! vec1 ['A 'B 'C 'D 'E 'F])

This creates a vector of 6 symbols and binds it to vec1. To select an element you can use the traditional vector-ref procedure:

(vector-ref vec1 3) ⇒ 'D

Alternatively, in Kawa you can use function-call notation:

(vec1 3) ⇒ 'D

You can also create a vector using the traditional vector constructor:

(! vec2 (vector 'A 'B 'C 'D 'E 'F))

There is one important difference between vec1 and vec2: You can modify vec2 by changing some or all of its elements. You can’t do that for vec1. (We say that vec1 is an immutable or constant vector, while vec1 is a mutable or modifiable vector.) To change an element use either the traditional vector-set! procedure, or function-call notation:

(vector-set! vec2 2 'Y)
(set! (vec2 4) 'Z)
vec2 ⇒ ['A 'B 'Y 'D 'Z 'F]
(vector-set! vec1 2 'Y) ⇒ throws exception

See Vectors for details and operations.

Java arrays and primitive vectors

See Using Java arrays for examples.

Indexing of general sequences

You can use function-call notation to index a generalized sequence, whether it is a list, vector, any java.util.List, native Java array, or string:

((list 'A 'B 'C 'D) 2)  ⇒ 'C
("abcdef" 3)  ⇒  ⇒
(! farr (float[] 1.5 3 4.5))  ;; native Java array
(farr 2) ⇒ 4.5

Note that indexing a list with an index i will be slow, since it has to step through the list i times. (So don’t do that!)

Ranges

A range is a sequence of numbers in order, spaced uniformly apart. Usually, these are (exact) integers that increase by one. The usual notation is:

[start <: end]

This is the sequence of integers starting with the integer start (inclusive) and ending with the integer end (exclusive). For example [3 <: 7] is the sequence [3 4 5 6].

The ‘<:’ is a keyword; the < is a mnemonic for the set of integers that are < the end value 6. You can also use <=: if you want to include the upper bound: [4 <=: 8] is [4 5 6 7 8].

You can use >=: or >: for a decreasing range. [5 >=: 1] or [5 >: 0] both evaluate to [5 4 3 2 1]. You can also specifify a step value: [1 by: 2 <=: 9], which evaluates to [1 3 5 7 9]. (Details here.)

Using vector and ranges indexes

If an index is a sequence of integers, the result is a new sequence (of the same type) selecting only the elements matching the index values. For example:

#|kawa:2|# (vec1 [3 5 2])
#(D F C)

In general, ((V1 V2) I) is (V1 (V2 I)).

You can use a range to create a slice - a contiguous subset of a list.

#|kawa:3|# (vec1 [2 <: 6])
#(C D E F)

A range is different from a vector integer in that you can use a range as the index in the LHS of a set!:

#|kawa:4|# (set! (vec1 [2 <: 4]) #(a b c d e))
#|kawa:5|# vec1
#(A B a b c d e E F)

Notice how the number of replaced elements can be different then the number of elements in the replacement value. I.e. you can do insertion and deletion this way.

#|kawa:7|# (! str1 (string-copy "ABCDEF"))
#|kawa:8|# (set! (str1 [2 <: 5]) "98")
AB98F

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Previous: Composable pictures

Next: Creating and using objects

Types and declarations

A type is a named value for a set of objects with related properties. For example, vector is the type for standard Scheme vectors. You can use a type to specify that a variable can only have values of the specified type:

#|kawa:5|# (define v ::vector #(3 4 5))
#|kawa:6|# v
#(3 4 5)
#|kawa:7|# (set! v 12)
/dev/stdin:7:1: warning - cannot convert literal (of type gnu.math.IntNum) to vector
Value (12) for variable 'v' has wrong type (gnu.math.IntNum) (gnu.math.IntNum cannot be cast to gnu.lists.FVector)
	at atInteractiveLevel$7.run(stdin:7)
	at gnu.expr.ModuleExp.evalModule(ModuleExp.java:302)
	at kawa.Shell.run(Shell.java:275)
	at kawa.Shell.run(Shell.java:186)
	at kawa.Shell.run(Shell.java:167)
	at kawa.repl.main(repl.java:870)
Caused by: java.lang.ClassCastException: gnu.math.IntNum cannot be cast to gnu.lists.FVector
	... 6 more

Using a type specification catches errors, and makes your programs more readable. It can also allow the Kawa compiler to generate code that runs faster.

You can use a type to check that a value is an instance of the type, using either the instance? function:

(instance? #(3 4 5) vector) ⇒ #t
(instance? '(3 4 5) vector) ⇒ #f

As a convenience, you can use a type-name followed by a “?”:

(type? val) == (instance? val type)

You can “call” a type as if it were a function, which constructs a new instance of the type. The following example shows how to construct a normal Scheme vector, and a Java array of ints:

|kawa:1|# (vector )
#()
#|kawa:2|# (instance? (vector ) vector)
#t
#|kawa:3|# (define x (int[] 1 2 3))
#|kawa:4|# x
[1 2 3]
#|kawa:5|# (instance? x int[])
#t

A fully-qualified Java class is a type name. So are the names of Java primitive types. So are Java array types, as shown above.

e.g. a JFrame is constructed by using its class name as a function:

#|kawa:6|# (javax.swing.JFrame )
javax.swing.JFrame[frame0,0,25,0x0,invalid,hidden,layout=java.awt.BorderLayout,
title=,resizable,normal,defaultCloseOperation=HIDE_ON_CLOSE,
rootPane=javax.swing.JRootPane[,0,0,0x0,invalid,
layout=javax.swing.JRootPane$RootLayout,alignmentX=0.0,alignmentY=0.0,border=,
flags=16777673,maximumSize=,minimumSize=,preferredSize=],rootPaneCheckingEnabled=true]

A type is a true run-time value:

(define mytypes (list vector list string))
(instance? #(3 4 5) (car mytypes) ⇒ #t

The define-alias form is useful for defining shorter names for types, like a generalization of Java’s import statement:

(define-alias jframe javax.swing.JFrame)

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Previous: Creating and using objects

Next: Exceptions and errors

Variables

You can declare a variable using a ! form. This takes a variable name, and an expression. It declares a new variable with the given name, and gives it the value of the expression.

#|kawa:1|# (! binary-kilo 1024)
#|kawa:2|# (! binary-mega (* binary-kilo binary-kilo))
#|kawa:3|# binary-mega
1048576

If you prefer, you can use define instead of !:

#|kawa:1|# (define binary-kilo 1024)
#|kawa:2|# (define binary-mega (* binary-kilo binary-kilo))
#|kawa:3|# binary-mega
1048576

The advantage of using define is that it is portable to other Scheme implementations. The advantages of using ! is that it is shorter; it generalizes to patterns (see later); and it guards against accidentally “shadowing” a variable by a nested variable with the same name.

A ! (or define) typed into the command-line defines a top-level variable.

You can also declare local variables, which are variables defined for a given block of code. For example, in the following code let is used to set up a local binding of x to 3: this does not affect the outer binding of x to 5:

(define x 5)

(let ((x 3))
  (display x))  ⇒ 3

(display x)     ⇒ 5

Alternative forms for defining local variables are let, let*, or letrec/letrec*.

The differences are in the order in which definitions are made. let evaluates all its definitions in the environment holding at the start of the let statement. In the following example, the local variables are defined using values from the global variables:

(define x 5)
(define y 2)

(let ((x (+ 2 y))  ; uses value of global y, i.e. 2
      (y (+ 3 x))) ; uses value of global x, i.e. 5
  (display (list x y)))  ⇒ (4 8)

let* instead evaluates each definition in the environment holding at the start of the let* statement, along with all previous local definitions. In the following example, y is now defined with the local value of x:

(define x 5)
(define y 2)

(let* ((x (+ 2 y))  ; uses value of global y, i.e. 2
       (y (+ 3 x))) ; uses value of local x, i.e. 4
  (display (list x y)))  ⇒ (4 7)

letrec/letrec* are similar, but allow the definition of recursive functions:

(letrec ((is-even? (lambda (n) (and (not (= 1 n))
                                    (or (zero? n)
                                        (is-odd? (- n 1))))))
         (is-odd? (lambda (n) (and (not (zero? n))
                                   (or (= 1 n)
                                       (is-even? (- n 1)))))))
  (display (is-even? 11)))   ⇒ #f

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Previous: Functions

Next: Composable pictures

Using non-Scheme languages for XML/HTML

XQuery language

Bundled with Kawa is a fairly complete implementation of W3C’s new XML Query language. If you start Kawa with the --xquery it selects the "XQuery" source language; this also prints output using XML syntax. See the Qexo (Kawa-XQuery) home page for examples and more information.

XSL transformations

There is an experimental implementation of the XSLT (XML Stylesheet Language Transformations) language. Selecting --xslt at the Kawa command line will parse a source file according to the syntax on an XSLT stylesheet. See the Kawa-XSLT page for more information.

KRL - The Kawa Report Language for generating XML/HTML

KRL (the "Kawa Report Language") is powerful Kawa dialect for embedding Scheme code in text files such as HTML or XML templates. You select the KRL language by specifying --krl on the Kawa command line.

KRL is based on on BRL, Bruce Lewis’s "Beautiful Report Language", and uses some of BRL’s code, but there are some experimental differences, and the implementation core is different. You can run KRL in BRL-compatility-mode by specifying --brl instead of --krl.

Differences between KRL and BRL

This section summarizes the known differences between KRL and BRL. Unless otherwise specified, KRL in BRL-compatibility mode will act as BRL.

In BRL a normal Scheme string "mystring" is the same as the inverted quote string ]mystring[, and both are instances of the type <string>. In KRL "mystring" is a normal Scheme string of type <string>, but ]mystring[ is special type that suppresses output escaping. (It is equivalent to (unescaped-data "mystring").)

When BRL writes out a string, it does not do any processing to escape special characters like <. However, KRL in its default mode does normally escape characters and strings. Thus "<a>" is written as &lt;a&gr;. You can stop it from doing this by overriding the output format, for example by specifying --output-format scheme on the Kawa command line, or by using the unescaped-data function.

Various Scheme syntax forms, including lambda, take a body, which is a list of one or more declarations and expressions. In normal Scheme and in BRL the value of a body is the value of the last expression. In KRL the value of a body is the concatenation of all the values of the expressions, as if using values-append.

In BRL a word starting with a colon is a keyword. In KRL a word starting with a colon is an identifier, which by default is bound to the make-element function specialized to take the rest of the word as the tag name (first argument).

BRL has an extensive utility library. Most of this has not yet been ported to KRL, even in BRL-compatibility mode.

XQuery language
XSL transformations
KRL - The Kawa Report Language for generating XML/HTML
Differences between KRL and BRL

Up: Working with XML and HTML

Previous: Generating HTTP responses